music
music
applause
applause
good night everybody
各位晚安
I actually took pictures of people for two weeks
我其實也很採照人兩個禮拜
Looking forward to today too
今天也很期待
Let's see this crazy horse
我們看這個瘋馬祖
Then I turned out to be Vice President Wang
那我原來王副院長
Wang Fan is the vice president
王凡是副院長
because of going abroad
因為出國
so please let me take
所以請我帶
There are so many people present today
今天出席的人特別特別多
I believe that everyone is interested in this topic
我相信大家都對這個題目
very very looking forward to
非常非常的期待
Then we also know that March
那我們也知道3月份
This Matsu, this incense
這個馬祖這個敬香
is a big event in Taiwan
是台灣的一件大事
I am very happy to invite Professor Zhang Xiong here today.
今天很高興可以請到這個張雄教授
come talk to us
來跟我們講
Reasons for All Taiwanese Matsu Beliefs
所有台灣馬祖信仰的原因
Like change, I probably know Mazu
跟變遷 像我大概知道媽祖
This Mazu will nourish the home these activities
這個媽祖會營養家這些活動
I don't know anything about his origins
關於他的淵源什麼我也不知道
So I am very excited about today's speech
所以對今天的演講也很起來
What about Dr. Zhang Xun, now he is
那張尋博士呢 是現在他是
Ethnic Researcher and Deputy Director
民族研究員也兼副所長
He is from the Department of Anthropology, National Taiwan University
那他是台灣大學人類學系的
Bachelor and Master
學士跟碩士
During his bachelor's and master's
那他在學士碩士期間
Taiwanese folk medicine
就已經以台灣民俗醫療
and religion etc.
還有宗教等等
as the subject of his research
作為他的研究題材
Then he went to Berkeley in the United States
之後他有到美國的Berkeley
get a doctorate
拿到博士學位
After returning to Taiwan, he continued
那回台以後他還繼續
Focusing on folk belief and folk medicine
在做民間信仰民俗醫療為主
to continue research
來繼續做研究
Of course, I did a lot of field research.
那當然也做了很多很多田野的調查
we can listen carefully today
我們今天可以細細來聽
Dr. Zhang is actually in the Department of Anthropology
張博士其實在這個人類學系
Probably anthropologists probably know him
大概人類學者大概都知道他
Well, he is still teaching human beings at National Taiwan University and National Chengchi University.
那他現在目前還在台灣大學跟政治大學教人類
I just found out when I was talking to him
我剛剛跟他談的時候才知道
The Department of Anthropology in Taiwan has very few students studying anthropology
這個台灣人類學系學人類學的是非常少
Then his topic today is to talk about the end of the Ming Dynasty and the beginning of youth
那他今天的主題是講明末青初
He is based on this book called Tianfei Dangerous Road
他是根據這個一本書叫做天飛險勝路
The basis here
這裡面的依據
Then he added his own research
然後他再加上他自己的研究成果
Then come and tell us all these origins and more
然後來告訴我們所有這些淵源等等
I think I won't waste everyone's time
我想我就不耽誤大家的時間
We are looking forward to Zhang Guoshi's speech
我們就盡情期待張國師的演講
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, Vice President Wang, for your introduction
謝謝王副院長的介紹
Thank you colleagues in the hospital
謝謝院內的同仁
And good friends outside the hospital
還有院外的好朋友
And our folks and elders in the Nangang area
還有我們南港地區的鄉親父老
I feel honored to be here
我覺得很榮幸可以來這邊
Let me report my research over the past few years
跟大家報告我這幾年的研究
Vice President Wang Fansheng About a month or two ago
王範生副院長大概一兩個月前
Notify me when I'm coming to give this speech
通知我說要來做這個演講的時候
I prepared a few topics for him to choose
我準備了幾個題目讓他選
Because this is a more general topic
因為這樣比較一般性的題目
I haven't been in touch for a long time
我已經好久沒接觸
As a result, Vice President Wang Fansheng chose this topic
結果王範生副院長他就選了這個題目
I think he probably also
我想他大概也
because he is more experienced
因為他比較有經驗
He's served the feast of knowledge for a long time
他服務了知識饗宴活動好久了
So he knows better
所以他比較知道
How can you resonate with the audience?
說怎麼樣可以跟觀眾共鳴
Choose an appropriate topic
選一個比較適當的題目
So I finally chose this topic
所以最後就選了這個題目
Feng Mazu
封媽祖
Then he explained to me that it is best to start from the most basic
然後他交代我說最好是從那個最基本的
Because Taiwan's Mazu belief we know is very prosperous
因為台灣的媽祖信仰我們知道很興盛
But he wants me to start from this most basic source
可是他希望我從這個最基本的源流
History, development, and the transition to the present
歷史 發展 然後到現在的這個變遷
make a report with everyone
跟大家做一個報告
So what I'm talking about today
所以今天我講的呢
If there are incomplete
如果有不周全的
Or you are in other parts of Taiwan
或者是各位在台灣其他地區
Because of the Mazu belief in the North, Central and South
因為北中南的媽祖信仰
may be slightly different
可能有少許的不一樣
What if something I said was incomplete?
如果有我講的比較不周全的呢
Give me advice when we can exchange time again
等一下可以再交流時間的時候給我指教
then i will sit down and talk now
那我現在就坐下來講
This is what we say is the one who sealed Mazu in March
這個我們說3月封媽祖的就是
Shawei Xiao Mazu
沙尾蕭媽祖啦
mean to say
意思就是說
Because March is probably Mazu's birthday
因為三月的時候大概是媽祖的生日
March 3rd
三月三日嘛
Are you before the third day of the third lunar month?
你在農曆的三月三日之前呢
you can go everywhere
你可以到各地去進鄉
Mazu Temples around
各地的媽祖廟
you are from the north go south
你是北部的人到南部去
Or people from your central part go to the south to enter the countryside
或者是你中部的人到南部去進鄉
That's because the whole month of March
那因為整個三月份啊
almost north and south
幾乎是南來北往
The big and small ones of the Mazu Temple I went to
到我出的這個媽祖廟大的小的
there are many activities
都有很多活動
Then the believers also enjoy it
然後信徒也都樂此不疲
So in Taiwan there is such a
所以在台灣就有這樣一個屬於
That is to say, Little Mazu Shawei
就是說沙尾小媽祖
That is in so many Mazu temples in Taiwan
那在台灣這麼多媽祖廟裡面
probably at present
大概以目前
Now I release these three temples
這我放出來這三個廟宇
only famous
唯比較有名
What about these three temples in 2010
這三個廟宇在2010年呢
also from our Ministry of Culture
也得到我們文化部
It is said that this is a national level
定為說是國家級的這個
Intangible Cultural Heritage
非物質文化遺產
So the Mazu Temple
所以就是說媽祖廟
it's not just religion
它不是只是宗教信仰
It has now become our Taiwan
它現在變成是我們台灣這個
items of intangible cultural heritage
非物質文化遺產的項目了
look from the right
那從右邊看過來
Baishatun Matsu enters the village
白沙屯媽祖進鄉
Does anyone know where Baishatun is?
有誰知道白沙屯在哪裡
ok, this one goes first
好,這位先說
Yes, Miaoli Tongxiao
對,苗栗通宵
In the middle, Dajia Mazu enters the village
那中間呢,大甲媽祖進鄉
This is probably on TV
這個大概你們在電視
The media knows that everyone
媒體都知道,大家
There is this black and black person
有這個黑黑黑倒的人士
The Beigang Chaotian Temple on the left
那左邊這個北港朝天宮
Do you know where it is?
也知道在哪個地方吧
Yunlin
雲林
Beigang Chaotian Palace, these three are very famous
北港朝天宮,這三個都很有名的
then let me ask a little more
那我再稍微問一下
Enter the countryside and follow around into the countryside
進鄉跟繞進進鄉
follow win mazu
跟贏媽祖
What's the difference
有什麼不一樣
why our culture is different
為什麼我們的文化不一樣
to choose these three
要選這三個
if all the same thing
如果都一樣的東西
why choose three
為什麼要選三個
Yes or no
是不是
What's the difference
有什麼不一樣
This is more subtle
這個就比較細微了
This is slightly different
這個就比較細微的不一樣
wait a minute we will talk about
等一下我們陸續會講到
If you take Baishatun as an example for offering incense
進香如果以白沙屯來說
His pilgrimage because he was from
他的進香因為他是從
he didn't make it that clear
他倒沒有講那麼清楚
He is from Beigang
他是從北港
share it
分享過來
So he goes to Beigang to enter Hong Kong every year
所以他每年去北港進香
It's like saying just go
等於說就是去
You can say this when you go back to your mother's house
回娘家可以這樣說
belongs to say
屬於來說
That big one
那大甲的
Wrap around into incense
繞進進香
Because he used to be before 1987
因為他以前在1987年以前
Dajia also went to Beigang to worship
大甲也是到北港去進香
But in 1988
可是1988年
He will no longer go to Beigang to enter Hong Kong
他就不再去北港進香
And what?
而且呢
In 1988 he changed to Newport
1988年他改去新港
after incense
進香以後
he added those two words
他增加了那兩個字
Wrap around into incense
繞進進香
so you know the difference
所以你就知道有不同了
When he went to Beigang
原先他去北港的時候
He is still the same as Bai Shatun
他還是跟白沙囤一樣
Jingxiang
就是只稱為靜鄉
But after going to Newport
但是去了新港以後
Beidajia added two words himself
北大甲就自己加了兩個字
called around Jingjing Township
叫繞靜靜鄉
around quiet words
繞靜的話
let's start with a little mention
我們稍微先提一下
I'll talk about it later
等一下會講細的
That is to say, a relatively high-ranking god
就是說一個比較高位的神明
he went to his jurisdiction
他到他的轄區
Or he went to the jurisdiction of a lower god
或者是他到比較低位的神明的轄區
to patrol
去巡視
go around quiet
去繞靜
as if we now our chief
就好像我們現在我們的長官
For example, the dean came to our Institute of Democracy
譬如說這個院長來我們民主所
Check out that jurisdiction
那個轄區去看一下
Let's see if you are doing your research well.
看你們有沒有在好好的做研究這樣
So Dajia Mazu went to Xingang
所以大甲媽祖他去到新港
He thinks he's better than Newport's
他自認為說他比新港的
Mazu is high
媽祖是高位
So he went around the Newport
所以他去繞靜新港
have this meaning
有這個意思
so he is above the name
所以他在名稱上面
He added those two words
他都增加了那兩個字
Then Beigang Chaotiangong only said that he was winning Mazu
那北港朝天公只說是贏媽祖
This is because the first two Baishatun and Dajia
這是因為前面兩個白沙屯跟大甲
He is every year before March 23 baby
他是在3月23之前每一年寶貝
So set off to Beigang or Xingang every year
所以每一年出發去北港或者新港
The time to enter the country is not certain
進鄉的時間不一定
As long as it is March of the lunar calendar
只要是農曆3月都可以
But come back to your own temple
但是回來回到自己的廟
Must be before March 23
一定要在3月23之前
so we can live
所以才能夠做壽
It's for Mazu's birthday
就是替媽祖做生日
But because Beigang Chaotiangong was in his own
但是北港朝天公因為是在自己
Xia District
境內霞區
He beat Mazu himself
他自己贏媽祖
It's him himself in this
就是他自己在自己的這個
Within the range of Xia District
霞區範圍裡面
Write to Mail Street
寫給就是郵街
So he didn't come to the country, so he didn't enter the country
所以他沒有到境以沒進鄉
Beigang is already
北港他已經就是
he is the boss
他是老大
He is the boss of many Mazu temples in Taiwan
他是台灣眾多媽祖廟裡面的老大
So he doesn't need to go outside to the countryside
所以他不需要往外面進鄉
he doesn't go either
他也不去
go around other borders
去繞別的境
he himself
他在他自己
Gap is
峽區就是
They call that Ben South Port and Ben North Port
他們稱為那個奔南港跟奔北港
Because Beigang used to be
因為以前北港
The other side of the district was probably called Bengang in the Qing Dynasty.
區那邊大概就是清朝的時候叫奔港
Later, because of the flood, it was divided into two
後來因為洪水分為兩
Two halves, so it is called Bennangang and Benbeigang
兩半 所以稱為奔南港跟奔北港
ok so we
好 所以我們
start with this
從這個開始
you know what to say
你們就知道說
There are many Mazu temples in Taiwan
台灣的媽祖廟很多
And the Mazu Temple in Taiwan
而且台灣的媽祖廟
there are some disputes between
之間有一些糾紛
right
對不對
I've heard that there are some disputes
已經聽到有一些糾紛了
Okay, let's start with the name of the city
好 那我們先從這個市名
It is the beginning of explaining the name of Mazu
就是解釋媽祖的名字開始
Generally we say worship Mazu
一般我們說拜媽祖
But you see a lot of temples
但是你又看很多那個廟上面
the name of the temple he wrote
他寫的那個廟的名字
It's about Thean Hou Palace
是寫天后宮
Then you look at him
那然後你看他那個
those beautiful red lotus
那些漂亮的那個紅蓮
or the whip
或者是那個排鞭
written above
上面寫的
Our Lady of Heaven
是天上聖母
And many believers
然後很多信徒呢
Especially when it comes to Beigang
尤其是到了北港
he doesn't call mazu
他不稱馬祖
not called diva
也不稱天后
He also does not call Our Lady of Heaven
他也不稱天上聖母
he called uncle
他稱伯啊
uncle
伯啊
call it a woman
就稱說是婆
Po he means like grandma
婆他的意思就是好像祖母的意思
That girl?
那娘嗎
It's rarely called like this in Taiwan.
在台灣比較少這樣叫啦
Generally speaking
一般來說
we say diva
我們說天后呢
In fact, in the 23rd year of Kangxi
其實是在康熙23年
Because the private man was in Kangxi for 22 years
因為私郎在康熙22年
Conquered Taiwan
攻克了台灣
Then report to Emperor Kangxi of the Qing Dynasty
然後上報清朝的皇帝康熙
that is
就是說
Because of the goddess Li Mo Niang
因為黎莫娘這位女神
help me get this taiwan
幫助我取得了這個台灣
So I hope this Emperor Kangxi
所以希望這個康熙皇帝
Feng Chi is the name of the goddess
封赤這個女神的名號
So Tianhou is Emperor Kangxi
所以天后是康熙皇帝
Only after the second wind is the Queen of Heaven
次風以後才叫天后
I didn't have this name before
之前呢沒有這個名字
That Mazu is a general folk name
那媽祖是一般民間的屬稱
what about my aunt
姑婆的話呢
She is called aunt in Meizhou Island.
是梅州島的人稱姑婆
Mazu is called aunt
稱媽祖為姑婆
So this is a very
所以這個是一個很
very personal teaching
很親屬化的教法
It is to regard Mazu as one's own relatives
就是把媽祖當成自己的親屬
aunt like this
姑婆這樣
what about mother
那娘媽呢
yes generally yes
是一般來說是
Minnan, a native of Fujian
敏南啊福建地區的人
A female name will be followed by a mother
的一種叫女性的名字後面會加一個娘媽
So there are names like this
所以有這樣的名字的
You will want to say Mazu
你們會想說媽祖
It doesn't matter whether this is mother or grandmother. Grandpa.
這個是媽媽是祖母也好啦祖先祖
It's the name of a goddess, isn't it?
這成為一個女神的名字是不是
A little
有一點
like
好像
Can't figure it out
想不通
It doesn't have his name on it either.
這上面也沒有他的名字啊
That can't be used to call other goddess mothers
那不可以用來稱別的女神媽
Why is it called Mazu?
為什麼叫媽祖
Ever wondered
有沒有奇怪過說
you hit worship mazu
你打擊拜媽祖
How could Mazu be called this name?
怎麼會媽祖是叫這個名字
ever wondered
有沒有奇怪過
because we know nothing but to say
因為我們知道除了說
Lin Moniang, her name is Mazu
林莫娘她的名字叫媽祖
We still have Chinese folk beliefs
我們還有華人的民間信仰裡面
many gods
很多的神明
We all use this relative to be called
我們都是用這個親屬成為來稱
You seem to say that the land lord calls him the lord
你像說土地公叫他公
And that Mr. Ping called him Mr.
還有那個平公叫他公
Then what about Beigong
然後呢貝公
The Hakka people call the Duke of Earth and the Duke of Bei.
客家人叫土地公叫貝公
Then Guanyin Bodhisattva is called Guanyin Bodhisattva in Buddhism
然後觀音菩薩在佛教叫觀音菩薩
But what is it called in folk belief
但是在民間信仰叫什麼
Avalokitesvara scolds
觀音罵
Then the Buddha's four schools imitate the Buddha
然後佛陀四家模擬佛
In Buddhism, it is called the four imitation Buddhas
在佛教叫四家模擬佛
In folk belief it is called not to do
在民間信仰叫不做
The ancestor came out
那個祖出來了
Avalokitesvara's scolding also came out
觀音罵那個罵也出來了
and some
還有有一些
those that
那些那個
yes blue cow horse yes
對 青牛馬 對
The star worshiped on the Qixi Festival on July 7th
那個七月七日那個七夕節拜的那個星
Green cattle and horses
青牛馬
There's some left
還有一些
Let me see if you can come up with an example
我看看你們還舉得出例子來嗎
to make up for
來 補作 補架
Restock here
這裡補架
That's my mother-in-law
那是婆姐
So sister also came out
所以姐也出來了
then buddy
然後好兄弟
Brothers
好兄弟
He's not a honey boy, isn't he a ghost?
他不是拍蜜仔 不是鬼嗎
what do you call him brother
你怎麼叫他兄弟
that's brother right
那是兄弟 對
and some of that girl temple
還有一些那個姑娘廟
That is to say, every girl who gets married dies
就是說每一結婚就去世的女孩子
if she thinks nothing
如果她嫌零了
Her temple can sometimes be called down
她的廟有時候可以叫下罵
It's just that she usually scolds very effectively
就是通常她很有靈驗的罵
also called her to scold
也是叫她罵
Actually she was a girl when she died
其實她死的時候是姑娘啊
but how to curse
但是怎麼變罵
how to change scolding
怎麼變下罵
Have you ever thought about these nouns
你們有沒有想過這些名詞
This is anthropologically
這個在人類學來說
That is to say, the gods of Taiwanese folk beliefs
就是說台灣民間信仰的神明
Because it bears the relative title of our Chinese
因為它帶有這個我們華人的親屬稱位
Then we know the gods of our folk beliefs
那我們知道我們民間信仰的神明
In addition to the natural gods such as the sun, the moon and the stars
除了說是日月星辰這些自然神
Others are animal gods
另外有一些是動物神
look at our fresh lake
你看我們的湖鮮
those animal gods
那些動物神
then there are some plant gods
然後有一些植物神
The big ball palace, the big tree palace
那個大球宮 大樹宮
There are also some artifact gods
還有一些器物神
That is to say, the door god, the god-maker
就是說門神啊 造神啊
this utensil god
這個器物神
In addition, most of the gods of folk beliefs
之外 大部分民間信仰的神明
People become gods after death, right?
都是人死後成神對不對
Since it was a human being
那既然它生前是人
So between it and believers
所以呢它跟信徒之間
is that we compare with
就是我們比較跟
if with christianity
如果跟基督宗教
Compared with Western Christianity
跟西洋的基督宗教對比起來
Chinese folk beliefs
華人的民間信仰
Because its god is actually a human being
因為它的神明其實它生前是人
But because he is a sage
但是因為他是先聖先賢
His personality is more noble
他的人格比較高尚也好
He deserves credit for national design
他有功於國家設計也好
So after his death he was
所以他死後被
Akabe
被兩個人赤蜂
Jade Emperor Red Bee
可以被玉皇大帝赤蜂
It can also be killed by the emperor red bee
也可以被人間的皇帝赤蜂
Then he became a god
然後他成神了
So this kind of god, this kind of personality god
所以這樣子的神明這種人格神
It is a person who becomes a god after death
是人去世以後成神的
Because he was the same as a human being during his lifetime
因為他生前等於是跟人一樣的
So when we call him
所以我們在稱呼他的時候
respect him call him
尊敬他 稱他為
Scolding Bo Gong Back Back Gong Back
罵 勃 功 背 背功
with this your relatives
就是帶有這個你親屬
It's a quasi-relative, a name like a relative.
就是準親屬 類似親屬的名稱
So there will be nouns like this
所以會這樣的名詞出現
good
好
Yes, because of Wen Zhugong
對 因為那個文助功
The Xingtian Gong in Taipei worships
台北的那個行天功他拜的是
Wu Enzu, you can also call him Duke Wenzhu
五恩祖 你也可以稱他為文朱公
So if he becomes a god, it's early
所以 如果他成神的時間很早了
You call him male because we know Lin Muliang
你就稱他公 因為我們知道林慕良
He became a god in the Song Dynasty until now
他是宋朝成神的 到現在
How could he not succeed after more than a thousand years
一千多年了 他怎麼可能不成
Scolding him can't be the solution
罵 他不可能是解
So this reflects another characteristic of folk beliefs
所以 這個又反映了另外一個民間信仰的特色
That is, after the god dies, he continues to age
就是 神明死後 他還繼續有年齡
Walking, he became a god in the Song Dynasty
在走著 他宋朝成神的
But as of now AD 2014
但是到現在 西元2014年
Then we'll count how many years he's gone
然後我們就會算 他走了多久幾年
he's in heaven he's still alive
他在天界 他還在活著
So we'll count his age
所以我們還會算他的這個年齡
Go on. He's probably still there.
還要繼續 他可能還在那邊休仙
still resting
還在休
ok, this is hard to press
好 這個很不好按
wow i turned it off
哇 我把它給按熄了
Okay, let's talk about it, okay, I was just talking
好 本身談 好 剛剛是說
Saying his name, why did he become Mazu?
說他的名字 為什麼會成為媽祖啊天后
Now let's talk about the century of his life
那現在說他的生平世紀
his original name
他本來名字
It's the name his parents gave him, Lin Mo
就是他父母給他的名字 叫林莫
Only two words Lin Mo
只有兩個字 林莫
Then we just mentioned that in Fujian, the southern part of Fujian
那我們剛剛提到說 在閩南地區福建呢
you just have to be a girl
你只要是女性女孩子
Usually there will be a "Niang" on the back
通常背後面會加一個娘字
For example, my name is Zhang Xun
譬如說我叫張詢
But you don't know that this Zhang Xun is a girl to a boy
可是你不清楚 這個張詢是女來男的
So when you die or write in the genealogy
所以當你去世或者寫在祖譜裡面的時候
Just add the word "mother", then you know that Zhang Xun is a woman
就加個娘字 那就知道這個張詢是個女的啦
Look at Lin Mo
你看林莫
He can be a man or a woman. This name
他可男可女啊 這個名字
you add a girl
你加個娘字
So you say Mazu's name is Lin Mo
所以你說媽祖叫林莫
Or call it Lin Mo Niang, both are right
或者叫林莫娘 都對
We are all
都對
Then according to the book I mentioned in the introduction
然後根據那本書就是我在簡介裡面有提的
A monk in the late Ming Dynasty and the early Qing Dynasty
明朝末年 清朝初年的一個僧人
a buddhist daughter
一個佛教的生女
Her name is Zhao Sheng
她叫趙聖
He said that the Tianfei who wrote it was in the book about Shenglu
他說寫的那個天妃寫聖路那本書裡面
In fact, there are many different versions of the book about Mazu
其實關於媽祖的書很多不同的版本
different opinions
不同的眾說紛紜
But Mazu has never been included in this official history
但是媽祖又從來不曾入這個正史
is the official history
就是官方的歷史
All these Mazu wrote holy roads
所有這些媽祖寫聖路啊
Concubine Tian, ​​what mother passed on?
天妃什麼娘媽傳啊
Our Lady of Heaven English Yuanliu Examination Many
天上聖母英國元流考很多
It's all folk notes
都是民間的筆記
It's all folk
都是民間的
Then if the version is different
然後版本不同的話
where they wrote his date of birth
他們寫的他的出生年月日出生地點
parents' names
父母的名字
Brothers have different names
兄長的名字都不同
That's why I said I'm going to order a copy
所以才說我要訂一本來說
lest you mess up
免得你們會亂掉
but there are different versions
但是有不同的版本
If you are interested in those
如果你們對那些有興趣
You can also find another
還可以另外找來看
Well, write the Holy Road according to that concubine who made the saint
好 根據那本那個造聖的那個天妃寫聖路
he is writing
他是寫說
What about Lin Mo, she started from birth
林莫呢她從出生開始
to the bright moon
到明月
full moon
滿月
We know that the Chinese have the ritual of doing the full moon?
我們知道中國人有那個做滿月的儀式嘛
when touched
摸摸過的時候
never cried
都沒哭過
Never cried from birth to full moon
從出生到滿月沒哭過
That's why we call him Lingmo
所以才稱他為靈末
don't cry, don't cry
就不哭啊 沒哭
Usually babies cry when they are born
通常小孩子出生哇哇哇落地就哭了
he didn't cry
他沒哭
But
可是
After Yagoshi
彌越之後
will speak
就會講話了喔
Don't say Mazu is dumb
你不要說媽祖是啞巴喔
someone said
就有人說
Mazu is dumb, I was wrong, if according to this book
媽祖是啞巴 我說錯了吧 如果根據這個書
He just didn't cry when he was born to one month old
他只是出生到一個月的時候他沒哭
not that he was dumb afterwards
並不是說他後來啞巴
Otherwise, how can he save people?
不然他怎麼救人呢
Yes or no
是不是
so
所以
This life is more unstable and more stable
此生自彌越不穩提升
Then he was born in the first year of Song Taizu Jiannong
然後他生的時間那是宋泰祖建農元年
March 23
3月23
Fujian
福建
Fuden
普田
death is in song taejoong
死是在宋泰中
September 9th
9月9日
Died on Meizhou Island
在梅州島死掉
according to the book
根據這本書呢說
Mazu's father's name is Lin Yuan
媽祖他的父親叫林苑
mother surnamed wang
母親姓王
The couple had a son
他們兩夫妻原來就生了一個兒子
It's Mazu's elder brother named Hong Yi
就是媽祖的哥哥 叫紅毅
There are Mazu and five older sisters
有媽祖還有五個姐姐
But what?
可是呢
Lin Yuan's father
林苑這個爸爸
He is this Putian
他是這個普田
It is Du Xunjian in Putian, Xinhua
就是新華府普田的都尋檢
Be a petty officer, something like a police chief now
做一個小官 類似像現在的警察局長
He thinks I'm middle-aged and only have one son
他覺得說我都中年了才只有一個兒子
What are you doing with so many daughters?
有這麼多女兒幹什麼
so many daughters are useless
這麼多女兒沒用
only one son
只有一個兒子
So what about this mother, this Wang family?
所以這個母親這個王氏呢
still want to get pregnant
還希望再懷孕
Let's see if I can have another son
看能不能再生個兒子
Then this sub-dream in Guanpusa
那就這個在關普薩的這個次夢
after conception
受胎以後呢
He always thought it was a man
他一直以為是個男的
But then she was born Mazu
但是後來生出來是媽祖
and then it's special
然後又是很特別的
When Mazu was born?
生媽祖的時候呢
what afternoon
什麼下午啊
this small
這個小
Great light shines brightly, and then the world is full of foreign lands
大光萬丈,然後異鄉滿世
There are many special phenomena
就是有很多特殊的這個現象
So he knew this daughter was probably special.
所以他知道這個女兒大概是很特別的
What about when Mazu was in her teens?
那在媽祖十幾歲的時候呢
There is a Taoist priest
有一位玄通道道士
when passing by his house
路過他家的時候
I think Mazu is a very smart girl
覺得說媽祖是很聰慧的一個女孩子
I taught him some secrets
有教他一些祕法
This is the Fulu, the painting of blessings, and the way of doing it.
就是這個福祿、畫福的啦、做法的
Then when Mazu was eight years old
然後媽祖在八歲的時候
Just into this private member of their dying family
就進他們這個臨世的家族的這個私屬
read Confucian books
讀儒家的書
So it can be said that this Mazu belief is in this book
所以可以說這個媽祖信仰在這本書來說呢
He integrated the beliefs of our traditional Chinese Confucianism, Secularism and Taoism
他是融通了我們傳統中國儒世道三教的信仰
Inside, it's a foundation
在裡面,這是一個基礎
That is to say
也就是說
It is a basis for the belief in Mazu to be so widely approved
是媽祖信仰可以這麼廣批的一個基礎
because most Chinese
因為大部分的中國人
You either believe in Confucianism or the world or the Tao
你不是信儒就是世就是道
so all acceptable
所以都可以接受
Mazu is acceptable
都可以接受媽祖
ok, what about now
好,那現在呢
Meizhou Island, let's take a look
梅州島 我們來看看
This is the Meizhou Island that I have photographed in recent years
這個是我這幾年去拍的梅州島
We know that during the Cultural Revolution, the CCP
我們知道中共在文革的時候
Destroy all, almost all temples
把所有 幾乎所有的廟宇都破壞
If it is not destroyed, it will also be confiscated
不破壞的話 也是變成充公
It's a warehouse, an army barracks, a factory or a hospital.
就是當倉庫 當軍隊的軍營 工廠 或者是醫院
Although Meizhou Island is off the mainland, it is on the sea
雖然梅州島是離開大陸 在海面上
But it was also not allowed to worship at that time
但是也是那時候不准拜
The whole island is occupied by the army
整個島是軍隊佔領的
So now this temple hat is all see you later
所以現在這個廟帽都是後來再見的
Probably only this part, this is the original temple
大概只有這部分 這個是原來的廟
These are all newly built next to this
這旁邊這些都是新建的
That was around 1970
那就是在1970多左右吧
there is one
就是有一位
The old lady of Meizhou Island
梅州島的老太太
she has a sense
她有感應
that is
就是說
She started to pray by herself
她就開始自己去拜
Later, with the consent of the garrison army
後來得到駐守的軍隊的同意
And it's on the mainland of Fujian
還有又在福建本土那邊
Some CCP cadres agree
有一些中共的幹部同意
So slowly preserved the temple without damage
所以慢慢的保存了廟沒有破壞
It was not destroyed during the Cultural Revolution
在文革的時候沒有破壞
Now such a big conquest
現在這麼大的徵修
Renovation and new construction
翻修新建
All Taiwanese believers donate money
都是台灣信徒去捐錢
mobilized
帶動起來的
So this is one of Taiwan's religions going back
所以這個是台灣宗教回去的一個
A big change for their local
對他們當地來說很大的一個變化
Okay, if you have sharper eyes
好這個如果眼睛看尖一點的人
You can see the birthplace
可以看到生天古蹟
When we went in the early years
早些年我們去的時候
There is no big incense burner in front
並沒有前面這個大香爐
And the three small incense burners above
還有上面三個小香爐
three legs
三個足台
this is later
這個是後來
Later home
後來家的
It was just this big rock
原先就是只有這塊大石頭
Then
然後
It is marked that Mazu is in
就標示著說媽祖是在
Born in Meizhou Island
在梅州島生天的
But is Mazu from Meizhou Island?
但是媽祖是不是梅州島的人呢
It has been the study of Mazu in the mainland
一直現在是大陸研究媽祖學
This has become a school
這已經成為一個學
scholars
的學者們
a point of contention
爭吵的一個點
What is Mazu
究竟媽祖是
Kamata
蒲田
That is to say, in mainland China, Fujian
也就是說在大陸本土福建
What about people in Kamata?
蒲田的人呢
Or is he from Meizhou Island?
還是他是梅州島的人
no way
沒辦法
they quarreled
他們爭吵不休
These scholars quarreled
這些學者爭吵不休
no definite evidence to prove
沒有確切的證據可以證明
but
但是呢
Death is death on Meizhou Island
死是在梅州島死
This is probably everyone's workers
這個大概是大家工人的
but raw words
可是生的話
we can only say
我們只能說
live in Kamata
生在蒲田
Because Meizhou Island also belongs to Kamata County
因為梅州島也屬於蒲田縣
because you see the ones in front of you
因為你看前面的那些
notebook novel
筆記小說啊
Local rule, local death
地方治啊地方死
It is written that it was born in this
寫的都說它生於這個
Min, Fujian
敏啊福建啊
but not sure
但是不確定
So it's probably a certainty to be born here.
所以在這邊生天大概是確定的啦
But life is
可是生是
born on the island
生在島上面
Or was it born on this land in Fujian?
還是生在這個陸地福建呢
it's not sure
這不確定
Then what I show you is here
那我給大家看的是這邊
this
這個
photo
照片
don't know
不清楚
has anyone been there
有沒有人去過
good
好
you can say this
你可以說這個
next to this
這旁邊嗎
The photo didn't come out
照片沒有出來的
old temple
舊的廟
good
好
anyone else thought of
還有沒有人有想到的
none of you went
你們都沒去
Those who haven't raised their hands haven't been there
沒有舉手的都沒去過
no, not footprints
不是 也不是腳印
There's a small entrance here.
這邊 有一個小入口好了
Then here it is 10 yuan if you put it together
然後這邊是搭起來就是10塊
Here is a small space
這裡等於是一個小空間
You can hide inside, it's that simple
你可以躲進去裡面 這樣簡單講
I didn't pay attention at first
我原先去沒有注意
Later, I found out why the teacher had some female believers hiding inside.
後來發現怎麼老師有一些婦女信徒躲進去裡面
Later, because there was no room for two people
後來 因為容不下兩個人
so wait till the next one
所以等到後來一個
I have a picture and someone else can come out and see it
我有一張照片另外有人可以出來可以看得到
When he squeezes out like this
等到他就這樣擠出來的時候
I also squeezed in to see what was inside
我也擠進去看裡面是什麼東西
found that he is a small platform
發現他就是一個小平台
Then there is a small incense burner inside
然後裡面有一個小香爐
Then I'll watch it, squeeze in and finish watching.
那我就看 擠進去看完了以後
i need to get out
我要趕快退出來
Because there will be someone waiting behind
因為後面還會有人要等著
I just watch what they're doing
我就看他們在做什麼
what about the women believers
那些婦女信徒呢
What about after she got in?
她鑽進去以後呢
she's over there
她就在那邊
Difficult to talk a lot
難難至於講一堆話
Let's talk, just talk to Mazu again
講話啦 再跟媽祖講話就是了
So we can imagine
所以我們可以設想 可以想
This should be a custom of their Meizhou Island
這個應該就是他們梅州島一個風俗
for example
譬如說
Since Mazu ascended to heaven
從這個媽祖升天以後
this place may really become a shrine
這裡可能真的成為一個聖地
He is offering a woman believer
他是提供了一個婦女信徒
A place to communicate with Mazu
跟媽祖溝通的一個地方
you see you hide in
你看你躲進去
if you don't look carefully
你如果不仔細看
you don't notice someone is here
你不會注意有人在這邊
I used to say that when I went there in 1987
以前我說1987年去的時候
I don't have this incense burner yet
還沒這個香爐
just a big rock
就是一個大石頭
Even the red word was added later
連這個紅色的字都是後來再把它
Trace it in red
描紅 把它描上去的
So that means
所以就是說
During the Cultural Revolution, no one noticed
文革的時候沒有人發現
There are still some religions secretly going on here
這邊還在偷偷進行著一些宗教
activities of faith
信仰的活動
So this Mazu belief is like this
所以這個媽祖信仰就是這樣
get down
纏純的下來
I use this to illustrate
我用這個也是來說明說
Compared with just so big, so red tail
對比剛剛那麼龐大 那麼紅尾
The palace here also has this small
的宮殿 這裡也有這種小的
A private place for believers to communicate with Mazu
私密的提供信徒跟媽祖溝通的地方
Because of a religious belief it will be passed down
因為一個宗教信仰它會傳承下去
have both
這兩方面都要有
There must be a big, public, national, official, legal, and recognized
要有大的 公的 國家 官方 合法 認可的
But there must be believers who can complain
可是也要有信徒可以親訴
A place where you can communicate with the gods, both of which are indispensable
可以跟神明溝通的地方 這兩個都缺一不可
Okay, so this one is after 1987
好 那這個是1987年以後
We are not talking about the statue of Mazu
我們不是說媽祖的神像啊
Are most of them destroyed?
大部分都被破壞了嗎
That's new
那這個是新做出來的
This shape is from Xiamen
這個造型是廈門的
A professor at the Art Department of Xiamen University
廈門大學藝術系的一位教授
Called Levi's, he designed
叫李維氏 他所設計的
This Mazu looks like
這個媽祖造型跟
You generally have seen the statue of Mazu, right?
你們一般 你們都看過媽祖神像吧
What is the difference between our Mazu statues?
我們的媽祖神像有什麼差別
written in Guangdong
就寫在廣東
ok, write again
好,你再寫
western roots
西方的根
he did it
是他做的
he came
他來的
right
對
And then there's his what
然後還有他的那個什麼
900,000 yuan pig
九十萬元豬
usually last able to cover
通常上次能夠遮擋
stay free
免留
yes very good
對,很好
This one came prepared
這位是有備而來的
Also, and
還有呢,還有
Listeners here, let me see
這邊的聽眾,我給我看看
Have you seen
還有沒有看出跟
We are usually in Taiwan
我們一般在台灣
what you saw in the temple
你在廟裡面看到的
Different statues of Mazu
媽祖神像不同的
Clam
蛤
What
什麼
what did the guest say
這位來賓說什麼
girly look
少女的造型
yes, his face
對,他那個面貌
not the same
也不一樣
correct
對了
color difference
顏色有差別
What are most of Taiwan's Mazu
台灣的媽祖大部分是什麼
black face even if not black face
黑臉的 即使不是黑臉
All in all a blur
總之一團模糊
And even if it's not a blur
還有即使不是一團模糊
the hat he was also covered in
他也被蓋的那個帽子
embroidered hat
刺繡的帽子
And the exemption that the gentleman just said
還有剛那位先生說的那個免留
That's the concubine
就是那個後妃
The emperors who passed the tradition to China
傳統遞至中國的那些皇帝
he has these
他有這些
because all the gods form
因為所有的神明的造型
In traditional China is the era of emperors
在傳統中國就是皇帝時代
This era with the imperial system of emperors
有帝制皇帝制度的這個時代
is regulated
是有規定的
what can you take
你可以拿什麼
what are you holding
手上拿什麼
what animals can be ridden on feet
腳上可以騎什麼動物
and the clothes you're wearing
還有你身上穿的衣服
wear on head
頭上配戴
there are rules
這都是有規定
It's all stipulated by Ribo
都是禮布來規定
Equal to our current Ministry of Culture
等於我們現在的文化部
stipulated
有規定的
you can't mess around
你不能亂來
If you mess around, you will be an evil god
亂來的話你就邪神
Then your temple is hidden words
那你這個廟就隱詞
I can send the army to tear you apart
就可以派軍隊把你拆散的
Then his appearance is indeed similar to ours.
那他這個造型的確是跟我們
What we saw in Taiwan Mazu Temple is different
我們在台灣媽祖廟看到的不一樣
one is color
一個是顏色
Normally gods don't make white
一般來說神明不會做白色
white is the color of chinese party
白色是中文聚會的顏色
Then why is the Mazu dancing statue in Taiwan
那為什麼台灣的媽祖舞像
easy to turn black
容易變成黑色呢
blackened
熏黑的
i have hinted
我已經暗示了
what i said already implied
我講的話已經暗示
easily blackened
容易被熏黑
blackened why
熏黑為什麼
Why don't you clean him up every year?
為什麼每年不幫他洗乾淨呢
right
對
Because if Mazu's face is black,
因為媽祖如果臉黑的話
It means he's obsessed
表示他相火忘聖啊
so many cigarettes every day blackened him
每天有那麼多香煙把他熏黑了
how can i wash it off
怎麼可以洗掉呢
like there's a joke that says
就像有一個笑話說
That teapot you make tea every day
你每天泡茶那個茶壺
Isn't there the word tea in it?
裡面不是有那個茶字嗎
do you want to wash him off
要不要把他洗掉
Of course not
當然不行啊
The teapot is useless after washing
洗了那把茶壺就沒用了
because of your accumulation
因為你那個累積出來
That is the historical value accumulated over the years.
那是成年累月累積出來的歷史價值啊
antiques are over there
古董就在那邊
Mazu statue in Taiwan
台灣的媽祖神像
You said 200 years, how do you prove it
你說200年 你說怎麼證明
If you take out a century-old Mazu
如果拿出一個百年媽祖
No one will believe her for 200 years, right?
說她200年 誰也不信 是不是
Well, there is one more thing this gentleman said just now.
好 還有一個剛剛這位先生說的
He is standing, Taiwan's Mazu
他是站的 台灣的媽祖
You don't stand in the temple, do you?
在廟裡面是不會站的 是不是
Then why doesn't our Mazu stand up
那為什麼我們的媽祖不站
Mazu in Taiwan does not stand
台灣的媽祖不站著
Don't you see farther by standing?
站著不是看得更遠嗎
do it kindly
做得有親切感
so how
所以怎樣
to sit
要坐著
yes he is standing or sitting
對 他是站著或坐著
It also involves where he sits, right?
還牽涉到他坐在哪裡 對不對
If you sit because there is no line below
你如果坐在 因為下面沒有排到
is on the top of the mountain
是在山巔
at the top of the mountain at the top of the mountain
在山巔 在山巔 刷墊
It's weird sitting on top of a mountain, isn't it?
坐在山巔也很奇怪吧
like our
好像我們這個
Our Powerpoint cut off my left and right
我們這個Powerpoint把我的左邊右邊切掉了
Just now that one is missing that, now this one is missing this
剛剛那張少了那個現在這張少了這個
The statue of Mazu is over here
這個媽祖站的那個像在這邊
It is the highest point in the entire Meizhou Island
就是在整個梅州島最高點
The highest point on the island stands here
那個島上最高點站在這邊
as a landmark
作為一個地標
as their landmark
作為他們的觀光地標
Because even if the CCP does not ban Mazu belief now
因為中共即使現在不取締媽祖信仰
but it does not endorse popular belief
但是它並不贊成民間信仰
You know its religious policy is
你們知道它的宗教政策就是
only legal five religions
只有合法的五個宗教
Folk beliefs are not legal religion
民間信仰並不成合法的宗教
But in Fujian it is to open the heart
但是在福建它為了打開心胸
Welcome the return of Taiwan compatriots
迎接台灣同胞歸來
It barely makes the Mazu belief in folk belief
它勉強讓民間信仰裡面的媽祖信仰
Just fight with one eye and close one eye
就爭一隻眼閉一隻眼
otherwise
不然的話
It could be Mazu belief in mainland China
它是可以就是媽祖信仰在中國大陸
Comparing is considered a cultural practice
比較是被認為是文化習俗
So as a landmark, the shape just now serves as a landmark
所以作為地標 剛剛那個造型作為地標
that i said
那個我說
The design by Professor Li Weishi from the Art Department of Xiamen University
廈門大學藝術系的那個李維世教授的那個設計
another one
另外一個
you both mentioned
你們也都提到的
He is carved in white granite
他是白色花鋼石雕刻的
Generally, our Mazu beliefs do not use stones to carve
一般我們媽祖信仰也不用石頭來雕
don't use stone to carve
也不用石頭來雕
Stone to carve can Buddha Bodhisattva in Buddhism
石頭來雕可以在佛教的佛菩薩
Gods not in Taoism
不在道教的神明
Taoism
道教
We know that the gods of Taoism should be consecrated
道教的神明我們知道要開光
Consecrate the inside of that idol
開光那個神像裡面啊
to put five treasures
要放五寶
Right, the statue is on the back of the statue
對不對神像就是在神像的這個背
Before sealing it, you need to put five treasures
要要封起來之前你要放五寶
five precious gold
五寶金
The picture of Jinmu fruit, that is realized, we need to put another one
金木水果圖啊那個實現還要放一隻
raw worm or bee
生的蟲或者蜜蜂
This makes that god like animate
這樣子讓那個神像有靈
Then, believers are communicating with the idol
然後呢 信徒在跟神像溝通
You said that you communicate with stones, what is the difference between pillars and wood
你說你跟石頭溝通 柱木不同有什麼差別
What is the difference between statues carved out of trees and statues carved out of stone?
神像用樹木雕刻的 跟用石頭雕刻的有什麼差別
There is a difference because
有差別 因為
It's more sensitive
比較能夠感應啦
This anthropology in this around the world
這個人類學在世界各地的這個
study of gods
對神像的研究就知道
If using stones use this
如果用石頭 用這個
What kind of stainless steel is that? Use this
那個什麼不鏽鋼的啦 用這個
It means that gold and steel are not bad, it means that this Buddha
它是表示金鋼不壞 就是顯示這個佛
it is a long time obsessed
它是一個 立久迷心的
it is long but with
它是長的 但是用
like communication
像溝通
like hinduism
像印度教
What you want is a sense, a sense
你要的是感應 一種感應
The induction between believers and God is Response
信徒跟神之間的感應 就是Response
trees are alive
樹木是有靈的
alive, alive
有活的啊 有活力的啊
Trees
樹木齁
With stone it won't...
石頭的話它不會...
If it is a stone, it will not be blackened
石頭的話也不會熏黑
the trees will be blackened
樹木才會熏黑
because it will go out
因為它會熄啊
trees will die
樹木會熄齁
so just that
所以剛剛那個
The shape of the statue of Mazu
媽祖像的造型
we just know
我們就知道
Mazu belief is now in mainland China
現在媽祖信仰在中國大陸
regarded as a landmark
被當作一個地標
A symbol of cultural tourism
文化觀光的一個象徵
anything else
還有呢
sea ​​peace goddess
海上和平女神
Mazu was in 1989
媽祖在1989年吧
called by the Chinese Communist Party
就被中共稱為
sea ​​peace goddess
海上和平女神
the goal is clear
目標很清楚
To maintain peace across the Taiwan Strait
要維持台海兩岸的和平
standing over there
站在那邊呢
where are his eyes looking
他的眼睛看向哪裡
I will go to...
我就特別去...
go to that...
去那個...
look carefully below
仔細下面看
Just looking towards Beigang
就是看向北港
Just looking at Taiwan
就是看向台灣啦
He wants to recruit Taiwan
他要招募台灣啦
Recruit Taiwan compatriots
招募台灣同胞
Wait a moment
等一下
We will finally put a POPPO inside
我們最後還會放POPPO裡面有一張
The roof of Chaotian Temple in Beigang, Taiwan
台灣北港朝天宮的屋頂
There is also a statue of Mazu that is exactly the same
也有一尊一模一樣的這個媽祖像
Two statues shaking each other
兩尊像的搖搖相望
ok , now let ' s talk about this
好,現在先講到這邊
Okay, then this is the Mazu who gave the loan
好,那這是送貸的媽祖
Originally, I could only get this in Taiwan
原先我在台灣只能拿到這樣子
Just turn around, I don't know who gave me a talisman
就是展轉吧,不知道誰送給我一個護身符
Then you see what the small lettering on it says
然後你們看到它上面那個小的字寫什麼
yes , your eyes are fine
不錯,你們的眼睛不錯
can pass that vision test
可以通過那個視力測驗
Wenfeng Palace in Putian, Fujian
福建普田的文豐宮
Then because of the convenience of the cross-strait connection, after going to the mainland
然後因為兩岸通的方便去大陸以後
I'll go and see
我就去看
This is really inside Wenfeng Palace in Putian, Fujian
這個就真的是福建普田文豐宮裡面
A statue of Mazu enshrined
所供奉的一個媽祖的神像
You can see that his appearance is also different from the current Taiwanese Mazu
你看他是造型也跟現在台灣媽祖不一樣
You see he is also carved in stone
你看他也是石頭雕刻的
And then he didn't have the nine exemptions just now.
然後呢他頭上也沒有剛剛那九條免留啊
Not wearing a hat either
也沒有戴帽子啊
This is the shape of Mrs.
這個是夫人的造型
Mazu in Song Dynasty
宋代的媽祖
We remember that we just said that Tianhou was only conferred in the 23rd year of Kangxi
我們記得剛剛說天后是康熙二十三年才封的
In the Song Dynasty, when Mazu had just passed away
宋朝的時候媽祖才剛剛去世的時候
Didn't he accumulate his merit so quickly?
他沒有那麼快累積他的功德嘛
So he was conferred the title of wife by the emperor
所以他被皇帝封呢還只封為夫人
So in the Song Dynasty, his shape was that of a lady
所以在宋代的時候他的造型是一個夫人的造型
ok then let's talk about it now
好啦那我們現在就來講
How does Mazu gradually accumulate his magical machine
媽祖怎麼樣慢慢累積他的這個神機
And slowly push his status up
還有把他的地位慢慢的推高
His team's magical machine is based on the record of the appearance of the concubine
他組的神機根據那本天妃顯身錄來說
These 16 are from his lifetime
有這16個是他生前
He began to show his magical power, power, and spiritual power while he was alive.
他生前就開始展現他的法力 威力 靈力
his ability
他的能力了
Because didn’t he get some secret techniques from Taoist priests?
因為他不是有得到玄通道士的交他一些祕法嗎
Then he can defend the prophet
然後他能夠衛補先知
So we won't talk about these one by one
所以有這幾個我們不一一說
Among them, for example, the old relative on the plane is the second one.
其中譬如說機上舊親就是這第二個好了
Whoops
哎呦
I'm so sorry
真抱歉我
I'm not familiar with this
我對這個不熟
The old relative on the plane is
機上舊親就是
The first one who was blessed by the police was the Xuan Taoist who took him to the blessing of the police.
第一個那個虧警得福就是玄通道士帶他去那個虧警福啊
Go to the wells one by one
去一個一個井啊
See the word floating up inside
看到裡面浮上來的這個字
This, this, these are the blessings, heavenly scriptures, and words drawn.
這個這個就是畫的這些福啊天書啊字
Then the old kiss on the plane is the girl he asked for in the past
然後機上舊親就是他在以前的女孩子要
want
要
Then one day when Mazu was imitating
然後有一天媽祖在仿之的時候呢
His original spirit went out to sea
他的原神出竅到海上去
because he heard his father and brother
因為聽到他的父兄
They are all in the countryside
他們鄉下都
not the country
不是鄉下
their fishing village
他們漁村
father and brother are fishermen
父兄都是漁民
fishing outside
到外面打魚的
his original god out
他的原神出去
Seeing his father and brother is a disaster
看到他的父兄就是落難
inside the shipwreck
在海難裡面
so he saved his father
所以他救了他的父親
But there is no way to save my brother
但是沒辦法救哥哥
so his brother
所以他哥哥
If you can't save it, you will die
沒救到就死掉了
but saved his father
但是救了他的父親
And there are many stories in the myth
然後神話裡面也講了好多
That Mazu can subdue these
那個媽祖可以收服這些
Ghost, Dragon King
鬼啊 龍王啊
And Yan Palace is their southern Fujian
還有燕宮是他們閩南
Poseidon
原來就有的海神
was also subdued by him
也被他收服了
So actually before Mazu
所以其實在媽祖之前
There are sea gods all over China
中國各地都有海神
God of water, god of river, right?
水神 河神 對不對
God of Rain and Friends of Water
雨神跟水友神
But Mazu subdued them one by one
但是媽祖一一收服
So get yourself up
所以自己就著狀起來
Up to now, most of us worship Matsu
到現在我們大部分拜的都是馬祖
Then the two ghosts Jiaying and Jiayou
然後這個嘉應跟佳佑這兩個鬼
It's the Clairvoyant Shunfeng we worship now
就是現在我們拜的那個千里眼順風
was also subdued by him
也是被他收服的
because these two monsters
因為這兩個怪物
At sea is always doing bad things
在海上就是常常做壞
So let the fishermen have no peace
所以讓漁民不得安寧
Also received by Matsu
也被馬祖收了
After speaking is after Mazu was born
語話以後就是馬祖生天以後
There are more than thirty miracle stories
還有三十多個神蹟故事
They are all accumulated in the Song, Yuan, Ming and Qing Dynasties.
都是宋元明清這樣累積下來的
different
不同的
The ones above here are probably from the Song Dynasty.
這邊大概上面的都是宋朝的
Then from here
然後從這邊啊
Nu Tao Ji Ruo this is probably the Yuan Dynasty
怒韜寄若這邊大概是元朝
Because the Yuan Dynasty had the Grand Canal
因為元朝有大運河了
then over here you see
然後到這邊你看
Taijian Zhenghe belongs to the Ming Dynasty
太劍正河就是明朝的
then to the qing dynasty
然後到清朝
Here, the latter three are related to Taiwan.
這邊 然後跟台灣有關係的是後面這三個
Then we will talk about it later
那我們仔細在後面講
So in that book
所以在那本書裡面
You can see a more detailed account of these myths
你們可以看到更仔細的對這些神話的說明
So Mazu belief will be so prosperous
所以媽祖信仰會這麼興盛
has its social background
是有它的社會背景
The first one was Mazu in the Song Dynasty
第一個 在宋朝的時候就是媽祖
We say he had some mana in life
我們說他生前就有一些法力
So he's accumulated some miracles
所以他已經累積了一些神蹟了
after he left
他走了以後呢
you see him in the country
你看他在國家方面
small do not say
小的不說
The small one is, of course, that he often has
小的當然就是他常常會有
Putting down the Han disaster brought some water
平伏漢災帶來一些水
large at the national level
大的在國家的層面
You see when he sends scriptures to battle
你看他送經交戰的時候
He helped the army of the Song Dynasty
他幫助這個宋朝的軍隊
be able to return safely or in blood
能夠平安的或歷血歸來
Then during the Yuan Dynasty we knew
然後元朝的時候我們知道
The newly built Grand Canal Chaoyun will bring this south of the Yangtze River
新建大運河朝運把這個江南的
Lost to Hebei
迷運到河北去
all apparition
都顯靈了
let this morning luck
讓這個朝運呢
very flat
很平服
arrived safely
很平安的到
Then when Ning Dynasty
然後寧朝的時候
the most important is
最重要的是
Zhenghe's seven voyages to Nanyang
正和七下南陽
The Western Ocean written here is Nanyang
這邊寫的西洋就是南洋
All are blessed by Mazu
也都得到媽祖的保佑
Then it came to the Qing Dynasty
然後這到了清朝
the biggest thing
最大的一件事
is to overcome Taiwan
就是克服臺灣
good
好
from
從
From this road in the Song Dynasty
從宋朝的這個路運
enemy is an ambassador
敵是一個大使
it's time to die
就是出死留求的時候
his ship was shipwrecked
他的船遇到海難
It was Mazu who saved him
那也是媽祖救了他
Then the battle between the two armies that sent gold
然後送金的兩軍的交戰
Then to the Yuan Dynasty and so on
然後到元朝等等
So in what I just mentioned
所以在我剛剛提的這個
Zhao Sheng is the monk
趙聖就是這位僧人
A monk in the Qing Dynasty called Zhao Sheng
清朝的一位僧人叫趙聖
In the book he wrote,
他寫的這本天飛險勝錄裡面
can see this mazu
可以看到這個媽祖
He has seen miracles
他屢見神功
so his official title
所以他官方的名號
Sealed one by one, we will show you his name later
逐次加封,等一下我們會給大家看他的名號
So his faith slowly spread from Putian, Fujian
所以他的信仰慢慢的從福建普田
To the north, to the south, to the whole of China
往北,往南,往整個中國
And because of Zheng He, he also went to Southeast Asia
還有因為鄭和呢,所以也往這個東南亞走了
The entire Mazu belief
整個媽祖信仰
Zheng He Xia Xiyang, look at the part he wrote about Zheng He
鄭和夏西洋,你看他寫關於那個鄭和的那一部分
Then this is another book, because he heard that Fei Shenglu's writing is not so detailed
那這是另外一本書,因為他聽菲神聖路那邊寫的沒那麼細
I used another book's
我用了另外一本書的
that is
就是
Gubu is Goufu, this talk is Goufu
古吹就是勾吹,這個談話是勾吹
In the first year of Yongle, Taijian Zheng and he went to Xianluo, which is now Thailand
永樂元年呢,太建鄭和他往仙羅,就是現在的泰國
After that, Kyoto University Shinyo
然後京大新陽
His boat was about to capsize, Zheng He just prayed silently
他的船快要翻覆了,鄭和呢他就默默的祈禱
I suddenly heard the sky and the moon floating in the sky
空中突然聽見這個天月浮空
I seem to see it, I seem to see it
好像看見,好像看見哦
God, standing on that stern
神呢站在那個船尾上面
top and then immediately calm down
頂端 然後呢馬上就風平浪靜
After returning, he told the emperor
回去以後他告訴皇帝
Then the emperor asked the former officials to worship this
然後皇帝就前官來拜這個
Mazu, so seven times later this Zheng and Xia Xiyang
媽祖 所以後來七次這個正和霞西洋
Every time before he goes to sea, he is in that Fujian
他每次出海之前都在那個福建
A port next to Fuzhou is called Changle Port
福州旁邊的一個港叫長樂港
Every time he goes to sea, he first worships this Mazu
每次出海他就先祭拜這個媽祖
Then we also know that in Southeast Asia
然後我們也知道在東南亞
About Zhenghe's century and some place names left by him
有關正和的世紀還有他留下來的一些地名
a lot that equals
很多 那等於
There are also scholars in Malaysia
在馬來西亞也有學者做
Survey of Mazu Belief Block 46
媽祖信仰的調查 46座
Except Malaysia Indonesia Singapore Thailand
除了馬來西亞 印尼 新加坡 泰國
There is Tianfei Temple, Tianhou Temple
都有天飛宮 天后宮
It can be said that as long as this is where the Chinese go
那可以說這個只要是華人所到之處
or this overseas immigrant
或者是這個海外移民
Probably will bring Mazu
大概都會帶著媽祖在
After being on the boat and landing safely on the shore?
在船上 然後平安落地上岸以後呢
Just take the little Mazu on the boat
就把船上帶的那個小媽祖
Just build a small temple and wait until you have the ability again
就蓋個小廟拜 等到你又有能力呢
Then slowly expand the temple
再把那個廟慢慢擴建
Therefore, in the study of Chinese immigrants, Chinese are overseas.
所以在華人就是海外這個華人移民的研究裡面
It is said that Mazu belief or Mazu Temple
有說媽祖信仰或媽祖廟
almost like a
幾乎可以像是一個
How to say this indicator is a sign
一個這個indicator 怎麼說 就是一個標誌
If you see a Mazu Temple in this place
你如果看到這個地方有媽祖廟
Of course you are sure there is a Chinese community here
當然你肯定這裡是有華人社區在
It is a bit like the spread of our current Christianity
就有點像我們現在的基督教的傳播
where is western culture
西方文化到哪裡
Its church is built wherever it is, right?
它的教堂就蓋到哪裡 對不對
What about before the Ming and Qing Dynasties?
那在明清之前呢
Chinese culture Han people's culture
中國文化 漢人的文化啦
where to
到哪裡
Where will the Mazu Temple follow?
那個媽祖廟就跟著到哪裡
So then I had the opportunity to go to America
所以後來我有機會去美國啊
go somewhere else
去別的地方
I just watched his China Town
我就看他的那個China Town
to see his Mazu Temple
去看他的那個媽祖廟
Guangdong in the early days
早期是廣東
Now they are all brought by Taiwanese to Matsu Temple
現在都是台灣人帶去的 馬祖廟
So you can also see different dynasties, different immigrants
所以你也可以看到不同的朝代 不同的移民
Wave after wave, they built different Matsu temples
一波一波的 他們蓋的馬祖廟也不同
Okay, but in the Qing Dynasty, this private man attacked Taiwan
好 但到了清朝這個私郎攻打台灣
Register with these three stories
有這三個故事登記
Kangxi was a private man for 21 years and 22 years
康熙21年 22年都是私郎
Get Tianfei's help when fighting Taiwan
打台灣的時候獲得天妃的幫助
So in 22 years after he conquered the hut
所以22年他攻克了蓬屋以後
Immediately, political and economic surrender in Taiwan
馬上就政經在台灣就投降了
So tomorrow is over
所以明朝就結束了
The Qing Dynasty got Taiwan
清朝就得到台灣了
So we say that Taiwan is in the whole of China
所以我們說台灣在整個中國來說
There are several reasons why Mazu belief is the most popular
是媽祖信仰最普及的有幾個原因
The first one is because you immigrated to Taiwan from Fujian
第一個就是因為你從福建移民到台灣
You want to cross the sea, so you probably want to worship Mazu
要過海嘛 所以你很可能就是要拜媽祖
Second, after you come to Taiwan
第二你來到台灣以後
From now on, you will first settle on this coast
以後你先是落腳在這個沿海
on the west coast
就西岸這邊
Haven't turned to the back mountain, Taitung, Hualien
還沒有翻到後山 台東 花蓮
You are on this coast from south to north
你在這個沿海從南到北
From Tainan Chiayi Changhua Lugang
從台南 嘉義 彰化 路港
All the way to Guandu in Taipei
一路上來到台北的關渡
You still rely on the sea in this coastal area
這沿海地區你還靠著海
So you still worship Mazu
所以你還會拜媽祖
Plus you look at this official
再加上你看這個官方
The official initiative
官方的這個提倡
The belief in Mazu was introduced to Taiwan
媽祖信仰傳入台灣
The earliest belief in our Mazu
最早 我們的媽祖信仰
came through Penghu
是透過澎湖來的
Because of course you are from mainland China
因為當然你從中國大陸
To get to Taiwan, you have to go through Penghu first.
要到台灣之間要先經過澎湖
So the Tianfei Palace in Penghu
所以澎湖的天飛宮
Now of course it's called Thean Hou Palace
現在當然叫天后宮
was the earliest in our gorges
是最早的在我們的峽區
Inside the Gap of the Republic of China
中華民國峽區裡面
The Tianfei Palace in Penghu is the earliest
澎湖的天飛宮是最早的
Then there is this in the island
然後本島裡面是有這個
The advertisement is now Chiayi Budai
廣告就是現在嘉義布袋
There is Tianfei Palace Tianfei Palace in the south of Antai
有天飛宮 安平台南的天飛宮
And Lulmen, Kaohsiung District, this is early
還有路爾門 高雄區 這是早期的
After the Qing Dynasty, this is probably the end of the Ming Dynasty
清朝以後這大概都是明朝明末
After the invasion, all the Matsu temples I saw in Taiwan
入侵以後呢 所有的台灣所見的媽祖廟
More than the total number of Mazu temples in mainland China
超過整個中國大陸媽祖廟的總數
Mazu is the patron saint of Taiwan
媽祖堪稱台灣的守護神
Then this is related to the entry of the private man into Taiwan
然後 這個跟私郎入台有關
Because after his 22 years of class
因為他22年課台以後呢
Emperor Kangxi criticized his private son, saying that he was of the fourth public class
康熙皇帝批評私郎說他四公交種
Because of the people in front
因為前面幾個人
His teacher, the private man's teacher can't beat him even if he bites
他的老師 私郎的老師咬起身都打不下來
Private man because he is a subordinate of Zheng Chenggong
私郎因為他是政成功的部下
But his family was killed by Zheng Chenggong
但是他的家人被政成功殺了
so he wants revenge
所以他要報復
Then he knows the strategy of political success
那他很清楚政成功的戰略
And the Ministry of Defense at sea
還有海上的部防
So he can successfully defeat the government
所以他就可以把政成功打敗
rather than politics
而不是政經
Because it has come to his son political economy
因為已經到了他的兒子政經
so he's proud
所以他很驕傲啊
But when the private man heard
但是私郎一聽到
Until Emperor Kangxi wrote about him
到康熙皇帝寫他那樣子呢
He can't be proud
他就不敢驕傲了
Hurry up and say this is the help of Mazu
趕快說這個是媽祖的助綻
So it can be said that he is
所以可以說他是
Then under the Chifeng of Emperor Kangxi
然後在康熙皇帝的赤峰底下
Mazu was named the highest queen
媽祖被封到最高的天后
Because Si Lang is afraid that he will be the master of his own achievements.
因為司郎怕他自己功高正主啊
Because you want to talk if Shiro is famous
因為你如果司郎是名默的想講
defected to the Qing Dynasty
投靠到清朝
If he follows the example of the dignified and proclaims himself king in Taiwan
如果他又效法正經在台灣自己自立為王
Kangxi is tired
就康熙可累了
He wants to send another general to beat him
他還要另外派個大將來打他
Tired
挺累的啊
So if Shiro wants to say
所以司郎如果願意說
I got help from Mazu
我因為得到媽祖的幫助
Then Emperor Kangxi is a bit like this
然後康熙皇帝等於有點這樣叫做什麼
This is one of Chinese politics and religion
這個是中國的政治跟宗教的一個
often appear
經常出現的
the emperor borrowed
就是皇帝藉著
Chifeng is a god
搬風赤風一個神明
Include this place
把這個地方收編進來
good
好
and what about this place
然後這個地方呢
No matter Taiwan or Fujian or Guangdong
不管是台灣或福建或廣東
you want
你要
become
成為
part of chinese culture
中國文化的一部分
is your local god
就是你的地方神明
accepted by the emperor
被皇帝接納
enter this
進入這個
The system of gods in the Central Plains
中原的神明的體系
Ministry of Rites
禮部的
inside four o'clock
四點裡面
So it's a two-way
所以這是一個雙向的
that is
就是
The Gods of Political Incorporation
政治收編地方的神明
It means that politics has included your place
等於政治把你這塊地方納進來了
that's what it means
是這個意思
good
好
then we will
那我們就
Introduce a few titles of Mazu
介紹幾個媽祖的封號
he from
他從
What about after Mazu died?
媽祖去世以後呢
Slowly seal him from Song High School
從宋高中開始慢慢封他
because he is not
因為他不是
Assist Song and Jin in the war
協助宋金交戰
And then you see, at first it was all just Mrs.
然後你看 最先都只是夫人
At this time, the lady has become a concubine
夫人到了這個時候成為妃了
Become a concubine and then arrive at the Yuan clan
成為正妃 然後到了元氏族的時候
become a concubine
成為天妃
Na Hongwu
那紅武
At the time of Hongwu, the holy concubine and then
紅武的時候 聖妃 然後
In the 19th year of Kangxi, she was still called Tianfei
康熙十九年的時候 還叫天妃喔
But in twenty-three years, because of Shi Lang's relationship
可是二十三年的時候 因為師郎的關係
Become him a diva, here's a jump
成他為天后 這邊是一個跳躍
It is to jump up Mazu's godhood to the highest level
就是把媽祖的神格往上跳到最高
all the goddesses all
所有的女神 所有的
Among the gods of Han people's folk beliefs, the most abundant god is Tianhou.
漢人 民間信仰的神明裡面最高豐好的就是天后了
Then the fifty-ninth year of Kangxi
然後康熙五十九年呢
be able to program it into four o'clock
能夠把它編到四點裡面
That is, the whole of China, as long as it is the Qing Dynasty
也就是全中國 只要是清朝
China ruled by
所統治的中國啊
Everything is fine, as long as there are believers in the temple built in your place
都可以 只要你地方觀蓋那個廟有信徒
You can watch the place and sacrifice yourself in Spring and Autumn
你就可以地方觀可以春秋自祭
can make this budget
可以編這個預算
Officials can compile this budget
官方可以編這個預算
Then he is the last, Mazu's last title
那他最後 媽祖最後一個封號
That is, in pastoral care for eleven years at the same time
就是在牧中同時十一年給
How many words do you look at
你看看多少個字
I did a good job of calculating it before I came here.
我剛來之前好好的把它算了一下
sixty-two characters
六十二個字
Then it was at this time, comrade
然後也就是在同志這個時候
According to the regulations of the Ministry of Rites, no more
禮部規定說不可以再增加了
No one can carry it down
已經沒有人背的下來
These are sixty-two characters
這六十二個字了
Right, you can add another sixty-four characters, no, no
對不對 你再加六十四個字 不行了 不行
So this is the rule of the Ministry of Rites and cannot be added.
所以這是禮部規定不能再加了
In the future, you can say that he is great
以後呢 你可以說他很偉大
He still has centuries of his constant apparitions
他還有世紀 他不斷的顯靈
But the emperor just can't add words
但是呢 皇帝就是不能再加字了
a group of four characters a group of four characters
這四個字一組 四個字一組
A group of four characters is
四個字一組都是
It's all because he has a certain apparition and contributed to the country
都是他有某某顯靈對國家有功的
A group of four characters like this
四個字一組這樣子
So this is the last one and it won't change
所以這已經是最後一個 不會再變了
I can't hold it anymore, I can't add it anymore
不能再憋了 不能加了
Okay, myths and rituals about Mazu
好 有關媽祖的神話跟儀式
We know that there is clairvoyance
我們知道 有千里眼瞬風文
Then he also subdued a lot of this fish, turtle, turtle, turtle essence
然後他還收服了很多這個魚蝦 鱉 鱉 鱉精
Vincent Rescue
文生救難
Besides, in terms of his rituals
另外呢 在他的儀式方面
There is this incense owner
有這個敬香業主
Owner, what I just explained
業主 那剛剛我的說明
You now understand why gods want owners
你們現在就了解為什麼神明也要業主
The god is not the mother of the god, why do you want the owner
神明不是變神的媽 怎麼還要業主
Because the gods of the Chinese people, the gods of folk belief are the same as people
因為中國人的神 民間信仰的神跟人一樣
So although Mazu became a god
所以雖然媽祖成神了
But he still has to go back to see his grandparents
但是他還要回去看他的祖 祖
ancestor
祖先
So also the owner
所以還要業主
Then there are others, these are all about Taiwan now
那還有一些 在 這是都是現在都只講台灣的
Zheng Chenggong is going to court, 1661
鄭成功在 要上案 1661年
When going to Taiwan from Nan'an, Fujian, passing through Xiamen
從福建南安經過廈門要來台灣的時候
At that time, the Dutch occupied Taiwan
那時候還是荷蘭人佔據台灣
Then he went ashore again from Lu Ermen
然後他又從陸耳門上岸
The sea never rises and cannot enter the shore
海水一直不上 進不了岸
He worships this Mazu
他就拜這個媽祖
Then after the sea buried
然後海水葬了以後
All the ships of his army may enter the port of Lummon
他的所有軍隊的船就可以進入那個陸耳門的港
So then he
所以後來他就
But this is all
不過這個都是
If you go to Lu Ermen to know
如果你們去陸耳門知道
There are two Mazu temples over there
那邊有兩個媽祖廟
One is called Notre Dame Temple and the other is called Tianhou Temple
一個叫聖母廟 一個叫天后宮
The two temples quarreled about who was the best gift
兩個廟就爭吵說誰是贈成功
Mazu
帶上來的媽祖
This is really the most special part of Taiwan's Mazu belief.
這個真的是台灣媽祖信仰最特別的
There are always two temples to contend for
永遠有兩個廟要爭
Who is he
他誰是贈同
That's like Dajia's mother, Chen Weiyu's mother said
那像大甲媽 陳偉瑜媽就說
When he wakes up in March, it starts to rain
他三月一起起叫開始就下雨
It just so happens that spring sowing needs rain
剛好就是春天播種需要雨
So all the farmers welcome this Yuyu?
所以就是大家都農民都很歡迎這個雨雨嗎
Then, like this white sand bucket that lasted all night
然後像通宵的這個白沙桶的寮開
Because there was no Hilo Bridge before
因為以前沒有希羅大橋之前
You really have to walk across the Zuoshui River
你真的就是要途步走過去這個佐水溪
After the Hiro Bridge
那希羅大橋有了以後
No one would be so stupid as to walk Zuoshui River
就沒有人會傻到要去走佐水溪
But it was around 2008
可是就是在2008年左右吧
The first one we just had
我們剛剛那個第一張
What you see on Powerpoint is that
Powerpoint上面看到的就是那個
White Sand Bucket book cover
白沙桶那本書的封面
Wait a minute, we brought a few copies and will give them to everyone
等一下我們帶了幾本會送給大家
The cover is those believers carrying the bridge
那個封面就是那些信徒抬著大橋
Just walk down to Zuoshui River
就走到佐水溪下面
Later, because we also had colleagues to follow
後來因為我們也有同事跟著走
I didn't leave that time
我那次我沒有走
They said that they really fully experienced the ancestors
他們說真的是充分體驗到當初先民
your ancestors
你的祖先們
The road to the countryside is hard and dangerous
進鄉的路是多辛苦多危險
What's more, let alone coming to Taiwan from Fujian
還有呢 更別說是從福建來台灣
how dangerous is that
那是多危險
Because Zuoshui River is basically dry now.
因為現在佐水溪根本就乾旱了嘛
no water
沒什麼水
but still terrible
可是還是很可怕
Even now there is no water in Sasui Creek
即使現在佐水溪沒有什麼水
nothing to be afraid of
沒什麼可怕了
still terrible
還是很可怕
Our colleague goes down
我們那位同事走下去
He said
他說
because of the river bed
因為那個河床
You walk by, of course there is sand
你從旁邊走當然還有沙地
until the center of the river
一直到那個河的中心的時候
There's mud under there
那底下都是爛泥巴
and that mud will go
而且那個泥巴會走的
will flow
會流動的
so you put your foot down
所以你這一腳踩下去
you don't know how deep it is
你不曉得它多深
And then bring a little water without being completely dry
然後還帶一點水又不是完全乾旱
your body can move
你的身體是會移動
But you can't step on it
但是你又踩不死
you can't step on it
你踩不到下面
so it's dangerous
所以是很危險的
What's more, when there was a lot of water
那何況當年那個水很多的時候
Now because Taiwan is relatively dry
現在因為臺灣比較乾旱
no water
沒有什麼水
so it's scary
所以是很可怕的
in those days they
在當年他們
we follow
我們跟著
whether to go with everyone
不管是跟大家走
Or follow Baishatun
或跟白沙屯走
You all know that I built your soil
都知道我建你的土
If you got this
你們如果有拿到這個的
You see, from Miaoli to Beigang
你看從苗栗走到北港
about three days
大概三天多
then take a day off
然後休息一天
Because Mazu is going back to her mother's house
因為媽祖要回娘家
Let her reunite with her mother
要讓她跟她媽媽合聚團員
rest for a day
休息一天
then walk back
然後再走回來
It takes nine days to go back and forth from Miaoli
從苗栗這樣來回要九天
If you start from Dajia, then eight days
那如果從大甲的話八天
Just walk on two legs
就用走的兩條腿這樣走
How many dangers are there in the middle
這中間要經過多少的危險
especially during the Qing Dynasty
尤其清朝的時候
every village
每個村莊
you out of your
你出了你的
your village your fate is in doubt
你的村莊 你的命運就未卜
Because there's a bandit, there's this bandit
因為有山賊 有這個強盜
What kind of aborigines made grass, all kinds
有什麼原住民出草 各種的
So it was not so easy for them to enter the countryside before.
所以他們以前並不是那麼容易進鄉的
Now it's because you're on the highway
那現在因為走的是高速公路
take the highway
走高速公路
Although all of Taiwan, we say that after Shawei Xiao’s mother
雖然全台灣 我們說沙尾肖媽之後
The whole highway is into the countryside
整條高速公路都是進鄉
But why doesn't Bai Sha Teng Da Jia have your name?
但是為什麼白沙騰大甲都沒有你名
Because he still keeps walking to this day
因為他一直到今天還是維持步行走路
One nine days, one eight days back and forth
一個九天 一個八天來回
so you can fully understand
所以你可以充分了解
People at that time had no roads and no lights at night
當時的人沒有路 晚上沒有燈
You're still walking there
你還是在那邊走著那種感覺
Just going to the countryside can let you
就是進鄉可以讓你
wait a minute we'll talk
等一下我們會講
Let you experience the most grassroots folk life
會讓你體會到那個最基層的民間的生活
so why now
所以為什麼現在
Every year until March everyone opens again
每年到三月大家又開
Starting to revive the tradition that says go
開始恢復這個傳統說要去走
Well, the process of coming to Taiwan is in Tianhui’s sketchbook
好 來台過程就是在天輝寫生錄裡面
There are a few myths about
有講到這幾個神話
It's all about Shiro
這都是跟詩郎有關的
This goes back to what we just talked about
這個回到我們剛剛講
This is the statue of Mazu worshiped in a typical Taiwanese Mazu temple
這是典型台灣的媽祖廟裡面拜的媽祖神像
right? sit down
對不對 你看坐著
He sat in that temple
他坐在那個廟裡面
Why is his Mazu banned?
為什麼 因為他媽祖不是被封了嗎
He was named Mrs. Tianhui
他被封為夫人 天輝
It's not drinking tea with nothing to do over there.
不是在那邊沒事幹的喝茶
He wants every opportunity
他要日禮萬機
Just like the view of this place in ancient times, every day is full of opportunities
就跟古代的這個地方觀一樣 日禮萬機
So he sat in the middle of that temple
所以他坐在那個廟宇的中間
These are little idols
這些都是小神像
If you go inside the temple and look at the big statue
如果你到廟裡面看那個大的神像
Is it the main hall or the Dingmiao?
正殿嗎 就是定廟嗎
Of course it is taller.
那當然比較高大 就是
As soon as you enter the temple, you can see how big he is
你一進去廟整個就看到他那麼大
he is the one
他就是
It's really a day-to-day job
真的是日理萬機
All believers enter through the gate of his temple
所有的信徒從他的廟門進來
was seen by him
都被他看到
He takes care of all your problems
你所有的問題他都要處理
This is usually smaller
這個是通常是小一點
It's just a statue, what kind of mother
就是一尊是什麼開台媽啊
What kind of Zwirner curse
一尊那種什麼卓納罵
It was enshrined on the boat
就是在船上供奉的
This is relatively small
這是比較小尊
Or someone else's
或者是人家的也可以
I just used it to illustrate
我只是用來說明說
The statue of Mazu in Taiwan looks like this
在台灣的媽祖神像是這樣的造型
And his eyes are hanging
還有他眼睛要垂連
hang down you don't get too dirty
垂著你不要髒太大
believer
信徒
He hangs down like this, you see
他這樣垂著表示你看
that is
就是
He is used to process formulas
他是用來處理公式用的
There are two forms of propagation of Mazu belief
媽祖信仰的傳播形式有兩種
The first is a spider web type
第一個是蜘蛛網型的
For example, from Meizhou
譬如說從梅洲
from the Song Dynasty
從宋朝傳出來
you can spread everywhere
你可以傳到各個地方
Quanzhou, Zhangzhou, Tianjin, Taiwan
全州啊 張州 天津 台灣
Another one is vertical
另外一個是垂
This is radiation
這個是輻射型的
The other one is a vertical Xi Po shape
另外一個是垂直的細埔形的
For example, from the Meizhou Ancestral Temple
譬如說從梅州祖廟
Then it splits into Beigang Imperial Palace
然後它分靈到北港朝廷宮
The Beigang Imperial Palace can also be divided into Dajia and Changhua
北港朝廷宮還可以分靈到大甲、彰化
Then Dajia and Zhengnangong can also split their spirits to Keelung
然後大甲、正南宮還可以分靈到基隆
So it forms such a system
所以它就形成這樣的一個埔系
It's Xi Po and Kinio's
就是細埔、基尼奧的
Zupu like our people
像我們人的祖埔
It's your Azu, Agong, Dad
就是你的阿祖、阿宮、爸爸
Then you can become a Pu family like you
然後到你這樣子可以成為一個埔系
It is also a way of spreading
這也是一種傳播方式
precisely because of this
正是因為這樣子
That's why we have incense and incense
所以我們才有進香跟分香
Because the incense is viewed from above
因為分香是從上面看下去
You go down
你往下面分
Fenxiang is a general term, generally speaking, Fenling
分香是統稱 一般說分靈
Because if you split your spirit, you can use the method of double body
因為你分靈的話可以用分身的方式
For example, carve another statue of Mazu
譬如說再刻一尊那個媽祖的神像
this kind of separation
這種就要分身
You can also go because you have no money
你也可以因為沒有錢去
Carve another statue of Mazu
另外刻一個媽祖神像
so you take a small
所以你就拿一個小的
Small incense bag, you can donate about 100 yuan
小香火袋 你大概捐100塊錢
You can get a small incense bag
你可以拿到一個小香火袋
You can take it with you, and then you go to San Francisco, USA
可以隨身帶在身上 然後你去美國舊金山啊
Immigration to Brasilia
去巴西亞移民
That incense bag is also called split spirit
那個香火袋那樣也叫分靈
Therefore, splitting spirits can use the method of avatars
所以分靈可以用分身的方式
Divide the statue, you can use the way of distributing incense
分神像 可以用分香的方式
Bring an incense bag, it's called split spirit
帶一個香火袋 都叫分靈
Then you wait until you settle down locally
然後你等到到當地落腳以後
You have the ability, you slowly built a temple
你有本事 你慢慢就蓋了一個廟
So you have to go back and make incense
所以你就要回去進香
want to go back for incense
要回去進香
So it's up to you to share the fragrance
所以往上面說你是分香下去
divide one by one
一個一個分下去
Like the grandparents, the fathers
好像那個祖輩啊 父輩這樣
to a son
到兒子這樣一個分
But up you go back to the owner
但是往上你就要回去業主
go back and offer incense
回去進香
Go back and worship your grandpa and grandpa
回去拜你的阿公阿祖
That's it
就是啦 也就是說
The universality of the gods of Chinese folk beliefs
華人民間信仰的神明的普世啊
He actually responds to people
他其實反應對應的是人
The drama of the human world
人的世界的這個戲譜
So in response to what we just said
所以又回應到我們剛剛說
why gods have that
為什麼神明有那個
What are you scolding, work, do
什麼罵啦 功啦 做啦
This is why he wants the owner
這種 所以他要業主
Then why did Da Jia give male workers a gift?
那為什麼以前大甲 贈男工
He said that when he went back to Beigang Imperial Palace, it was the owner, Jingxiang
他說回去北港朝廷宮是業主 敬鄉
Okay, so here are a few pictures I took early on.
好 那這是幾張我早期拍的照片
In 1986, Dajia
在1986年 那時候大甲
you see what is written here
你看這邊寫的
What about this male worker who is now in Dajia?
這個現在大甲的贈男工呢
don't like me posting this photo
就不喜歡我放這個照片
He said that we have long since stopped going to Beigang to enter the countryside
他說我們早就不去北港進鄉
We are now going to Newport to look in the mirror
我們現在是去新港照鏡
Why are you still posting this old photo?
你還放這個老照片幹什麼
But history can't be erased
但是歷史不能抹滅啊
Look here, it's written as a gift to the male worker
你看這裡寫贈男工天上
Our Lady goes to Beigang, enters the countryside and enters the valley
聖母往北港進鄉開入谷
This is the headshot
這是打頭炮的啦
It's Pioneer
就是開入先鋒的
There is still a series of teams going to the countryside
往下還有一場串的那個進鄉隊伍
Then why do you say you want to cut it?
那為什麼說要割壞
is the fire owner
是火業主
These nouns are all said by Zheng Nangong himself.
這些名詞都是鄭南宮自己說的
not what i said
不是我說的
because of an anthropological survey
因為做人類學調查
We just use that local term
我們就是用那個local term
That is to say, the locals, the reporters
就是說當地人 報導人
his vocabulary
他所用的詞彙
It's not what we put in academic vocabulary
這不是我們用學術詞彙加上去的
They said they were going to hang up
他們說他們去掛會
then go to the owner
然後去業主
The owner is of course bye
業主當然就是拜
In that era before 1987
在那個年代來 1987年之前
1986 was his penultimate time
1986是他倒數第二次
He stopped going to Beigang in 1988
1988他就不去北港了
he cut the fire
他去割火
I can only speak with my mouth
割火我只能用嘴巴講
i didn't put a photo
我沒有放照片
that is
就是
Where is the incense burner in Zheng Nangong?
大家鄭南宮的那個香爐呢
After being brought to Beigang, the two incense burners were put together
帶到北港以後兩個香爐放在一起
Then the monk will start from
然後那個和尚會從
Use that for the incense burner in Beigang
北港的香爐用那個
soup sticks
湯條啊
Just shake three scoops to this
就搖三勺到這個
Everyone's Incense Burner
大家的香爐
every spoonful
每搖一勺呢就
What Guotai Minan
什麼國泰民安
good weather
風條雨順
Wishing in six places, bringing the five shares of harvest like this
六處心望,五股豐收這樣子帶過去
Then everyone quickly put away his incense burner
然後大家就把他的香爐趕快收起來
put it in a packing list he brought
放到他帶來的一個箱單
It's just a wooden seat and a box to put it away.
就是一個木座的一個箱子裡面收起來
That's his whole pilgrimage
那個就是他整趟進香
The core value of the group spent tens of millions of yuan
團花了幾千百萬元的核心價值所在
I'm going to bring this incense back
就要把這個帶回來的這個香火
Bring back the spiritual power of incense ash and take everyone
香灰靈力帶回去帶大家
After taking it back
帶回去以後呢
Take this incense ash from Northport
把這個從北港帶來的香灰
use a smaller spoon
再用一個更小一點的勺子
Put them one by one into the whole Dajia
一個一個放到那個整個大甲
There are about a dozen incense burners in Zhannan Palace
湛南宮大概有十幾個香爐裡面放回去
This is called cutting fire
這樣叫做割火
Then Ye Zu is Ye's
那葉祖就是葉的就是
The meaning of the Mazu of Beigang Chaotian Palace
那個北港朝天宮的媽祖的意思
that this is along the way
那這個是沿途
these are old photos
這都是老照片
Talk about Nenjiu coffee along the way
沿途說嫩久咖
this nenjiu coffee
這個嫩久咖
Nen Jiuka is the believers along the way
嫩久咖就是沿途的信徒這邊
Just arrived in Changhua
就是到了彰化吧
Then they kneel down along the way
然後他們沿途跪下去
wait for that big teacher
等一下那個大教
just pass on them
就在他們的身上這樣過去
Believers say that they can pray for peace
信徒說這樣可以求平安
like that
好像那個
like x-ray
照X光一樣
like that now what do we say
好像那個現在我們說什麼
like tomography
斷層掃描一樣
Then this clairvoyance
那這千里眼瞬風聞
then he
然後他
all mirror images
所有的鏡像團
Consisting of small groups one by one
由一個一個的小的這個團體所組成
what about each group
每個團體呢
all have their own characteristics
都有他的特色
like this show flag team is
像這個秀旗隊是
All made up of vowed women
全部都是還願的婦女組成的
Plus he has that T-babe
另外他有那個T貝
It's the cycling team.
就是自行車隊啊
motorcycle team
摩托車隊啊
that ox cart
那個牛車馬車
lorry truck oil cable car
貨車卡車油纜車
There are various teams
就有各種不同的隊伍
So walk for several kilometers like this
所以綿延幾公里這樣走著
The women who made the vow
那這些還願的婦女
because you make a wish if you say
因為你許願如果說
Son returns from military service
兒子當兵順利回來
son admitted to university
兒子考上大學
Or my mother-in-law recovered from illness
或者是我的婆婆生病好了
Or the harvest of my fields
或者是我家的田地豐收
any house is fine
什麼院都可以
Then say that I pay my respects to my hometown
然後說我以敬鄉為還願
Then you will come to Jingxiang
那你就要來敬鄉
Then this is across the Hiero Bridge
那這個是過這個希羅大橋
Then every local
然後每到當地
the local temple will come to welcome
那個當地的廟就會來迎接
it's a bit of a parody of that
這就有一點模仿那個
we handed to china times
我們遞至中國時代
It's the time when the emperor goes on tour in micro-clothes
就是皇帝微服出巡的時候
then everywhere
然後到了各地
The magistrate will come to welcome
那地方官就要來迎接
well, that's exactly
好,就是完全
Folk belief is a copy
民間信仰就是一個翻版
This one from our Huang Dynasty period
一個我們黃朝時期的這個
A replica of the bureaucracy
官僚體制的一個翻版
Then this is Beigang
那這個是到了北港
Beigang
北港
I didn't bring another photo
我沒有帶另外一張照片
This is the former Beigang and the other
這個就是以前北港還有那個
The little train in Tangchang, Taiwan
台灣唐廠的那個小火車
one fifth
五分之一
The five-point car is a small train specially used to transport
五分車就小火車專門用來運送
The dry slag sugar from Tangchang
那個唐廠的乾渣糖的
Then to Beigang
然後到了北港
The locals they organized this Dajia
他們籌組這個大甲的當地人
Head Township
所組成的這個頭鄉
Teams from Two Townships and Three Townships
二鄉 三鄉的隊伍
He's here to sponsor this whole race team
他是來贊助這個整個競鄉團
all these shows
所有的這些演藝表演
The performances are sponsored by Sanxiang of Touxiang
表演都是由頭鄉的三鄉贊助
So these three relative
所以這三個相對
they have some rights
他們就擁有一些權利
For example, wait until it is equal to Grandma Zu
譬如說等到等於阿媽祖
Well
呃
After cutting the fire, when you want to go back to Dajia?
割火完了要回大甲的時候呢
they can plug in
他們就可以插頭鄉
like when you celebrate new year
就像你們過年的時候
Rushing to Xingtiangong Plug Township means the same thing
搶著去行天宮插頭鄉那個意思一樣
That's also a worthwhile study
那也是一個值得研究的
What is Plug Township?
什麼叫插頭鄉
Why Plug Township
為什麼要插頭鄉
Why Gardens Need Plug Boxes
花園為什麼要插頭箱
what did the plug box get
插頭箱拿到了什麼東西
good
好
Then in 1988, if you see them, they won’t go
那1988年你看他們就不去
Beigang is going to Xingang Public Office to open Taiwan Mazu
北港是到新港公廳公開台媽祖
good
好
So we start from that temple ranking dispute
所以我們從那個廟宇的排行順序之爭
We can analyze the community identity of that civil society
我們可以分析那個民間社會的社區認同
and historical memory
還有歷史記憶
Let's wait and see if we have time to talk about the details
這個細節等一下看看有沒有時間講
These are the two temples, Xingang Beigang
就是這兩個廟啊新港北港
They are arguing about why Beigang chose this new port in the end
他們在爭吵北港為什麼最後選擇了這個新港
good
好
That's what I'm reporting to you
前面就是我向各位報告這個
Origin and development
源流跟發展
Then there is his relationship with modern society
再來就是他跟現代社會的關係
Mazu belief is one of our folk beliefs in Taiwan
媽祖信仰在台灣是我們民間信仰的一個
What is very special is that he followed the changes in Taiwanese society.
很特別的就是他跟著台灣社會的變遷來走
And it fits well
而且是配合的很
close he is not a dead faith
密切 他不是一個死的信仰
He is not locked in a temple
他不是一個關在廟裡面
A Faith Known Only to Believers
只有信徒才知道的一個信仰
He walked with the pulse of the entire Taiwanese society
他是跟整個臺灣社會的脈動一起走的
So let's just look at these five aspects
所以我們只看這五個方面好了
just in politics
就是在政治方面
We have been since 1987
我們從1987年
Why did he still go to Beigang in 1987?
那個為什麼他87年還去北港
I won't go there in 1988
88年就不去了
Because of his October 1987
因為他87年的10月
1987 happened to be
87年剛好是
Do you remember Mazu
你們記得媽祖
died in 987
987年去世了
so
所以
Died in AD 987
西元987年去世
1987 coincided with the 1000th anniversary of the birth of other languages
1987年剛好他語化生天1000年紀念
What about the Meizhou Ancestral Temple?
那個梅州祖廟那時候呢
They just came to open up at the time of Deng Xiaoping
他們剛好鄧小平的時候來要開放
So come back to Taiwan
所以要臺灣回來
Ancestral Temple in Meizhou is like Mazu temples all over the world
梅州祖廟就像世界各地的媽祖廟
just say love
就發出情鐵說
welcome
歡迎你們
Come back to celebrate the 1000th anniversary of the birth of Mazu
回來慶祝這個媽祖語話生天一千年紀念
Then most of the Mazu temples in Taiwan will not be moved after receiving the love iron
然後台灣大部分的媽祖廟收到了情鐵就不感動
hide it
把它藏起來
only Dajia
就只有大甲
because he was
因為他那時候
want to string together
想要串起來啦
Dajia
大甲
Local people We know that all temples in Taiwan have places
地方人士我們知道台灣的廟宇都是有地方的
Favorable people are supporting
有利的人士在支撐的
They are regardless of politics, economy and religion
他們是不分政治經濟宗教
are tied together
是綁在一起的
So what about the big guys?
所以大甲的人士呢
They want to string together they use this
他們要串起來他們就借著這個
go
去
Meizhou Township
梅洲進鄉
So with this invitation letter, they held a meeting in the temple.
所以拿著這個邀請函呢他們就在廟裡面開會
Decided to say yes we're going to take the risk
決定說好我們要冒險過去
Take the risk, but you can't just go there at that time
冒險過去可是那時候不能直接過去啊
So they flew to Japan first
所以他們就先坐飛機到日本
Then
然後
Then to Shanghai From Japan to Shanghai and then to Shanghai
再到上海從日本再到上海然後上海再到
Meizhou
梅洲
good
好
Because at that time the two sides of the strait had not yet opened
因為那時候兩岸還沒開通
So after going to Meizhou in this way
所以藉著這個方式去到了梅州以後
Really spent the night there back to Liang's house
真的在那邊回梁家過了一個晚上
Everyone is terrified, those directors and supervisors of Dajiazhen Nangong
大家都心驚膽跳那些大甲陣男宮的董監事們
17 people
17個人吧
I was terrified and wondered if I would be left there by the CCP
心驚膽跳的不知道會不會被中共留在那邊
What if I can't come back to Taiwan in the future?
以後回不來台灣怎麼辦
So before going back to Taiwan
所以要回台灣之前呢
They hurriedly told the Legislative Yuan that Liu Songfan was still at that time
他們就趕快跟立法院那時候還是劉松凡
when the legislator
當立法院長
Liu Songfan is from Dajia
劉松凡是大甲人
His younger brother is Liu Songlin
他的弟弟叫劉松林
It's a person from Mazu Temple
就是媽祖廟裡面的一位人士
So deploy it first
所以先部署好
Taiwan's airport can't come and arrest us
台灣的機場不能來把我們抓起來
Even he is afraid that the CCP will keep him
就是他也怕中共留他
But when he returned to Taiwan, he was also afraid that the Taiwan government would arrest him
但是他回到台灣也怕台灣的政府抓他
Because you are fat like this, aren't you?
因為你這樣是通肥啊是不是
So fix everything here first
所以先把這邊也都打點好
I'll be back when I'm done
好了就回來了信好
Anyway, what happened back then
反正那時候的事情
You still have newspapers when you go back
你們回去看報紙都還有
no drama
不講戲的
so
所以
That is, October 1987 at that time
也就是那個時候10月1987年的10月
Dajia sneaked away to Meizhou to enter the countryside for the first time
大甲第一次偷跑去梅洲進鄉
You'll be fine when you come back
回來以後還好平安無事
Then he started promoting
然後他就開始宣傳了
That is to say, I am now the leader of the Mazu Temple in Taiwan
就是說我現在是全台灣媽祖廟的龍頭
Why?
為什麼?
If I win back the statue of Meizhou
如果我贏回來的梅洲神像
I know the latest
我分明最新的
The latest Meizhou idol in Beigang is from 200 years ago
最新的你北港以前的梅洲神像是200年前的
Now this is the latest Meizhou idol
現在我這個是最新的梅洲神像
most fierce
最有凌厲
just won back
才剛剛贏回來而已
right
對不對
The fiercest
凌厲最大
so he said my
所以他說我的
My Mazu is the most respectful
我的媽祖是最有凌認
all Taiwan
所有台灣
Welcome all Mazu temples in Taiwan to come to my side
歡迎台灣所有媽祖廟都來我這邊
into the countryside
進鄉
In Beigang, you just scold Dajia and say you are Sudianwang
那個北港你就罵大甲說你素典旺族
Sudianwang
俗典旺族
you last year
你去年
not last year
不是去年
In March of this year, you still came to my side to enter the countryside
今年3月你還來我這邊進鄉
Also called my owner into the countryside
還稱我業主進鄉
You went to Meizhou in October and came back
你現在10月去了一趟梅洲回來
You are Sudianwang
你就俗典旺族
I'm Meizhou
我是梅洲
you are directly
你是直接 也就是說
Dajia wants to climb from granddaughter to daughter
大甲從孫女要爬到女兒的地位
I didn’t say that because we didn’t just talk about Meizhou
這樣沒說 因為我們剛剛不是說梅州
Then Beigang and then Dajia?
然後北港 然後大甲嗎
Now Dajia is going up one level
現在大甲要往上爬一層
He wants to climb from the status of granddaughter to the status of daughter
他從孫女兒的地位要爬到女兒的地位
It's like this, of course Beigang won't let it go.
等於是這樣 北港當然不放啊
Then Dajia wants to make a comeback now
然後大甲他要 他現在想要出頭嘛
He must. Later, Beigang told you not to come.
他一定要 後來北港就說你不要來了
Su Dian Wang Dajia told me that I will not go
蘇典王大甲來說 我才不去
i'm your sister now i'm not yours
我現在跟你是姊妹 我可不是你的
I'm not your daughter. He's not going.
我不是你的女兒啦 他不去了
Okay, after two people tear their faces apart
好了 兩個人撕破臉以後
That Xingang came out to be a Japanese room boss
那個新港就出來當和室老
There is only one bridge between Xingang and Beigang
新港跟北港只差一條橋
Xingang said then you don't have to move
新港說 那你不用動
Anyway, when the troops of the brigade are brought down from Dajia
你反正大隊的人馬從大甲帶下來的時候
Just tilt it this way at the last point
就只要在最後一點 這邊歪一下就好
It went to Xingang
就歪到新港來了
So 1988 was the second year and the Newport was ready
所以1988年就第二年馬上新港就準備好了
Open all elementary schools and clean them
把所有的國小都打開打掃
all toilets
所有的廁所
That's very busy
那個很忙碌的啊
in a few days you will
幾天之內你就要
You see tens of thousands of people
你看有幾萬人
In 1988, there were about 60,000 pilgrims
1988年的時候大概6萬進香客
You have to prepare food and drink for 60,000 people
你要準備6萬人的吃喝拉撒稅
It's not easy
是不容易的啊
Xingang Usual
新港平常
have you ever done such a thing
做沒有做過這種事
Anyway, let's go like this
總之呢就這樣過去
ok
好啦
So since that year
所以從那一年呢
Every year since 1987, everyone sees
1987開始以後每一年大家看到
Didn't he get locked up for this?
他沒有因為這件事被關起來嘛
So he goes back every year once a week for
所以他每年都要回去每周一次為了
The spiritual power of the Mazu who can maintain him
能夠維持他的那個媽祖的靈力
That's the one that hit us in Taiwan
那也就是這樣衝撞了我們台灣的那個
that
那個
cross-strait policy
兩岸的政策
Then I want you to know about the political part behind this, because although the Kuomintang, the Democratic Progressive Party, and the Kuomintang
那這後面政治的部分我想各位知道因為雖然歷經國民黨民進黨又國民黨
But cross-strait policy
但是兩岸政策
It was indeed initially opened by religious exchanges
最初的確是藉著宗教交流打開的
Only then did the small three links
才有後來的小三通
Daisan Street
大三通
and other exchanges
還有其他的那些交流
good economical
好 經濟方面
I use Xingang cultural and creative industry as an example
我是用新港文創產業來說
we know in 1994
我們知道在1994
That is, the document will propose the overall construction of the community
就是文件會提出社區總體營造
In the future, every village in Taiwan
以後台灣的每個鄉村
We must develop our own industry by ourselves
就要自營自己發展自己的產業
Many industries are not well developed
很多產業不好發展
later they trial and error
後來他們嘗試錯誤
Many later discovered that religion
很多以後發現那個宗教
Especially with the temple as the center of a community
尤其是以廟宇來做一個社區的中心
Can gain the trust of most villagers
可以取得多數村民的信任
because you see
因為你看
In a village, if I say I want to build a cemetery furnace
一個鄉村裡面如果我說我要蓋一個墳化爐
simply put
簡單的說
Build a burial furnace
蓋一個墳化爐
Can't cover it for several years
幾年都蓋不起來
Same goes for building a road why
蓋一條道路也一樣 為什麼
Yes, no benefit
對啊 不同利
Different parties cannot cover
不同黨派沒辦法蓋
But in the end, let's go to the front of the Mazu Temple, baby
但是最後說我們到媽祖廟前面寶貝
see if you want to cover
看要不要蓋
So in other words religion plays a role
所以也就是說宗教扮演的一個
interracial
誇族群的
A relatively high status of the quali group
誇利團體的一個比較高超的地位
So I found some places later
所以後來發現好些個地方
The community uses the temple as a
社區以廟宇來作為一個
The center of overall creation of community development
社區發展總體營造的中心
can do something
還可以做成一些事
Environmental friendly
環保
Like the nuclear market in Gongliao
像貢寮的核市場
We also know that repeatedly
我們也知道反反覆覆的
Covered and stopped and covered
蓋了又停停了又蓋
Then there is a temple in Gongliao
然後貢寮當地有一個廟宇
Jiaorenhegong Mazu Temple
叫人和宮媽祖廟
His Mazu
他那尊媽祖
later known as the anti-nuclear mother
後來就被稱為反核媽
Because every time they go anti-nuclear
因為每次他們要反核的時候
that is
就是
As I just said, in your community
剛剛說的嘛你一個社區裡面
Half of the people are in favor of Gai and Song
有一半的人贊成蓋和宋
because you'll get some benefits
因為你會拿到一些好處
Half of the people opposed to capping the market
有一半的人反對蓋合市場
The two factions are at loggerheads
兩派的人相爭不下
Finally, the man and the public Mazu Temple
最後把那個人和公的媽祖廟
just carry it out for a parade
就抬出來遊行
That is to say, Mazu is the mother of the sea
就是說媽祖是這個大海之母
It's our country goddess
是我們的這個鄉土女神
We want to love our family and our country
我們為了要愛家愛國
love our community
要愛護我們的社區
So it is to carry Mazu out for a parade
所以就是把媽祖抬出來遊行
Her name is Fanhe
她叫反和嘛
Well, another example would be
好 那另外一個例子是
DuPont in Lukang
鹿港的那個杜邦
We know that DuPont is an American
我們知道杜邦是美國的一個
brand factory
牌子的工廠
He chose Lukang to build
他選了鹿港來蓋
But at that time in Lukang
但是鹿港那時候
Everyone in Lukang is against it
全鹿港的人都反對
Because of their what-that-waste
因為他們那個什麼那個廢料
I'm not ready today so I can't tell you the details
我今天沒有準備講不了細節
will pollute the local
會污染當地
So they also carried out the Tianhou Palace in Lukang
所以他們也是抬出鹿港的天后宮
That is, there are two Tianhou Temples in Lukang
就是鹿港有兩個天后宮
the old one
舊主宮那個舊的那個
I also carried that mother out
也是把那個媽祖抬出來
then say
然後說
To protect our country
為了愛護我們的鄉土
So Mazu has become synonymous with native land
所以媽祖變成是鄉土的代名詞
rural pronoun
鄉土代名詞
It is Mazu who protects us
就是媽祖是保護我們的保護神
She is our Mother Earth
他是我們孕育大地母神
He is our Ocean Mother Goddess
他是我們的海洋母神
It's like becoming a spokesman for the country
就是變成是鄉土的一個代言人這樣子
Can represent the community as a speaking symbol
可以代表社區作為一個發言的象徵
words of education
教育的話
so many years now
現在累積這麼多年
You watched the TV or media reports
你們看那個電視或者是媒體的報導
Every time I come to the country
每次到了進鄉時候
You can see the studios of literature and history around the world
你可以看到各地文史則工作室
And Yan Xiying, a teacher in the countryside
還有鄉村的那些教師顏錫瑩
Zhong Primary School Teacher
鍾小學老師
They will all choose to be a person who understands the local culture
他們都會選擇作為一個認識鄉土文化的
an opportunity to participate in the country
一個機會參加進鄉
Then along the way, I got to know some grassroots people in the rural areas of Taiwan.
然後沿途認識一些台灣鄉村的基層的
items of some cultures that have disappeared
已經消失的一些文化的項目
In addition to talking about the bottom
另外除了說底層的啦
There are also 10 or 20 master and doctoral dissertations
碩博士論文也有一二十本了
Just now we met an Englishman in the audience
剛剛我們還在聽眾裡面認識有一位英國
where is the female graduate student who came
來的一位女研究生在哪裡
Emily
Emily
Emily,where are you?
Emily,where are you?
He said
他說
He said he was here to write Mazu's master's thesis
他說他就是要來寫媽祖的碩士論文
There are three doctoral dissertations that came to Zhongyuan to ask me for help
來中原請我幫忙的博士論文有三篇
are all
都是
you just know
你就知道
The Mazu culture in Taiwan has already become an issue in international academic circles
這台灣的媽祖文化已經是在國際學術界成為一個議題了
Because you can use it to communicate with other cultures
因為你可以拿來跟別的文化
compare with
做比較
Like the Islamic pilgrimage
像那個伊斯蘭教的朝聖啊
catholic pilgrimage
天主教的朝聖
Pilgrimage around the world can be used for comparison
世界各地的朝聖都可以用來做比較
it's educational
這是教育方面
In addition, in terms of culture, we are cultivating
另外在文化方面我們培養中
Humanities and Intangible Cultural Heritage
叫人文還有非物質文化遺產
especially now in 2009
尤其現在2009年
Year 2009
2009年
Originally, Taiwan wanted to bring Mazu belief to UNESCO
本來台灣就想把媽祖信仰拿到 UNESCO
Unesco to apply for world-class
聯合國的教科文組織去申請世界級的
Intangible Cultural Heritage
非物質文化遺產
But this news was known by the mainland
但是這個訊息被大陸那邊知道了
they did it
就由他們做了
Of course they do it faster
他們當然就做得更快了
They got him up in a month or so
他們在一個月左右把他做起來了
it exploded
就爆出去了
explosion explosion
爆爆爆爆
There are several people who educate people from the place of Kamata
從那個蒲田的地方教育人士有幾位
meat industry
肉業
The meat industry wrote those required documents
肉業寫了那些需要的文件
Then those people hurried to live in Beijing
然後那幾個人還趕快住到北京去
Stay in a hotel
住旅館
How to communicate with that central-level official
跟那個中央級的官員溝通怎麼樣寫
Must be on within a few days
幾天之內就把必須上
The application documents are all written
申請的這些文件全部就寫好了
And because the mainland came to call
還有因為大陸來號召
Look at the basic information about Taiwan
你看台灣的這些基本資料
Malaysia Singapore Hong Kong
馬來西亞 新加坡 香港
Information on Mazu Temples in various places in Macau
澳門各地的媽祖廟的資料
He just took it
就被他一收
Wow, he represents the Mazu temples all over the world
哇 他就代表全世界的媽祖廟
Year 2009
2009年
successfully applied for that world-class human
就成功的申請了那個世界級的人類
Intangible Cultural Heritage
非物質文化遺產
So now Mazu belief is in mainland China
所以現在媽祖信仰在大陸
In addition to saying that it is to welcome Taiwan compatriots back
除了說是為了歡迎台灣同胞回去
another one
另外一個
Another nice one
另外一個這個好聽的
The impressive title
冠冕堂皇的這個title
intangible cultural heritage
就是非物質文化遺產
you just hold this
你只要是拿著這個
this hall of fame
這個名堂啊
this name
這個名號啊
What reconstruction are you applying for?
你去申請什麼重建
Reconstruction, renovation, addition
復建 加修 加裝
usually right
通常就準了
The local view is fine
地方觀就準了
So Taiwan is also
所以台灣也被就
back again
又倒回來
From 2009 to the present also rewind
從2009年到現在也倒回來了
Many Mazu Temples in Taiwan
台灣的很多媽祖廟
I saw that I don't want to be just a tree religion
看到說 那我不要只是樹株宗教
I can also tree culture customs
我也可以樹株文化習俗
So now many Mazu temples in Taiwan have also added this item
所以現在台灣許多媽祖廟也增加了這一項
It is non-household cultural heritage to apply
就是非戶籍文化遺產 去申請
So there is the 2010 we just talked about
所以有剛剛我們說的那個2010年
Beigang Baishatun and Dajia
北港白沙屯跟大甲
Just registered with the Ministry of Culture as Taiwan's national
就在文化部登記為台灣的國家級的
Non-household cultural heritage
非戶籍文化遺產
Then last year and now the new year is only March
然後去年 現在新的年才3月
Last year last year Newport Toyota Palace also applied
去年 去年新港豐田宮也申請
but not yet
但是還沒有過
So it is conceivable that many temples have to apply
所以可以想見很多廟宇都紛紛的要申請
This is Xingang 2010
這個是新港2010年
I said this Haiji
我說這個海紀
Because Mazu died on September 9th?
因為9月9號不是媽祖去世嗎
After we treat Mazu as a god in Taiwan
在台灣我們把媽祖當神以後
We don't remember his Haiji
我們就不記他的海紀
Because you know when you hear Haiji
因為你一聽海紀就知道
didn't catch you
沒有勾起了你
The bad memory says he fell into the sea and died
那個不好的回憶說他是落海而死
right
對不對
Otherwise, why Haiji?
不然幹嘛海濟呢
If he becomes an immortal, he will go to heaven and you will pay back
他都成仙都往天上去你還
Haiji
海濟
that is not
那不是
but
但是
this is taiwan
這是台灣
Because we were in the Qing Dynasty
因為我們在清朝時候
Accepted Mazu is already a god
接受的媽祖已經是個神了
But in Fujian, it is especially a good port
但是在福建尤其閑良港就是
The place where Mazu was born
媽祖出生的地方啦
Didn't I just say that mainland scholars have been arguing all the time?
我剛剛不是說大陸學者一直吵嗎
One of them is that Xianlianggang is the place where Mazu was born.
其中有一派就是說閑良港是媽祖出生地方
people of this faction
這一派的人
It is because Xianlianggang still has the temporary ancestral hall of Mazu after all.
就是因為閑良港畢竟還有那個媽祖的臨時宗祠
had his first temple
有他的第一座廟
There's a lot of him in those uniforms
有他的很多的那些什麼受警服
those are
就是那些
that well
那個井啊
Many monuments are still there
很多的古蹟都還在
so
所以
Then they will hold this Haiji
然後他們還會舉行這個海濟
September 9
9月9號
So when you come here to do your research
所以你到這邊去做調查的時候
You can feel that Mazu is a person
你可以感覺到那個媽祖就是一個人
one person
一個人
he
他
A moral person, a very wise person looks like this
有道德的人 很賢慧的人這樣子
you just feel that he is alone
你就是感受到他是一個人
Unlike the Mazu we accept in Taiwan
而不像台灣我們所接受的媽祖
It's a god, it's already a god
就是是一個神了 已經是個神了
But Xingang Toyota's Taiwan
但是新港豐田公司台灣的
In other words, if the mainland is going to hold a big event
也就是說現在大陸如果要舉行大的活動
There must be Taiwanese believers to sponsor
一定有台灣的信徒去贊助
This is for sure
這是一定的
Napu Tianshi Wenfeng Gonggang
那普天士文豐公綱
We are not talking about the Song Dynasty Mazu
我們不是說那尊宋代媽祖
Are you enshrined here?
供奉在這邊嗎
You see, it is also a donation from Taiwan compatriots
你看也是台灣同胞的捐款
Let the whole Wenfenggong be rebuilt again
讓整個文豐公又重建起來
Otherwise, his enclosure
不然本來他那個圍樓
The wooden palace that is already a three-story walled building
已經是圍樓三層樓的那個木造的宮殿
no one dares to climb up
沒有人敢爬上去
But now you see rebuilt like this
但是現在你看重新建造成這樣
That's why I put a piece of Hainan Island because
那這是我放一張海南島是因為
Hainan Island because its ass is remote
海南島因為它屁股偏遠
so their thean hou palace
所以他們的天后宮
There is also the word Minyue here
這裡還有閩月兩個字
That is to say, there are some differences from Taiwan.
也就是跟台灣有一些不同的地方
For example, its Minyue does not have a vent
譬如它的閩月沒有洩鬥
Unlike Taiwan's Minyue, who will vent
不像台灣的閩月會洩鬥
That can be compared with Thean Hou Palace
那可以和視天后宮
In addition, their folk beliefs
另外是他們的民間信仰
Although it is said that Mazu applied for it in 2009
雖然說2009年媽祖申請到了
flying material cultural heritage
飛物質文化遺產
But in such a remote place as Hainan Island
但是在海南島這麼偏遠的地方
What to manage? Intangible cultural heritage
管理什麼飛物質文化遺產
The builder in my place is going to come in and build a building
我這個地方建商要進來蓋大樓了
How many billions can you earn if you get the building?
拿到大樓可以賺多少個億
Why do I still have Mazu Temple?
我還有媽祖廟幹嘛
guess guess
猜猜猜
We are probably the only one who can see the Thean Hou Temple
我們這個大概唯一可以看到還有天后宮
Everything else is guesswork.
其他都是猜的亂七八糟的
This is also the size of the ancient mainland
這也是中古大陸這麼大
The whole face of its Mazu belief
它的媽祖信仰的那個整個面貌
is different very different
是不同的很不一樣的
In Meizhou Island, because of the support of Taiwanese believers
在梅州島因為有台灣信徒的資助
so it recovers well
所以它恢復得很好
but in other regions
但是在其他地區那裡
different situations
情況都不同
This is about creativity
這個是說到文創
It is the current cultural and creative industry
就是現在的文化創意產業
That is to say, the combination of Mazu Temple
也就是說馬祖廟結合
Cultural and creative industries are used to develop his economy
文化創意產業用來發展他的經濟
Then Xingang Deputy Senior Worker's
然後新港副年工的
There is a characteristic of Mazu Temple that says their Tiger Lord
馬祖廟有一個特色說他們的虎爺
is very famous
是很有名利的
So they also did this
所以他們也做了這種
In addition, this is environmentally friendly
另外這個是環保
Xingang people call the foundation to do environmental protection
新港人叫基金會做的環保
planting natural rice
栽種自然米
Then green their local Xingang Hong
然後再綠化他們當地的新港香
cultural and creative industries
這種文化創意產業
These are made of incense
這些是用香做的
incense made
香做出來的
This is the new shape
這也是這新的造型
also made with incense
也是用香做的
It is to become a new product in their local area
就是變成他們當地的一個新的產品
How many people want to buy incense now
現在有多少人要買香
If you go for two hundred yuan, no one will buy it.
一去兩百塊 都不一定有人要買
Because many people don't say goodbye now
因為現在很多人不拜拜了
But those self-confessed masters
可是那些自相的那些師傅啊
And those SMEs?
還有那些中小企業啊
Did you say you want him to close the door?
你說要他關門嗎?
Mostly closed, yes
大部分關門 沒錯
or go to the mainland
或者是去大陸
Or buy that Vietnamese case
或者買那個越南的箱
Then come to Taiwan for processing
然後來台灣加工
this is the cheapest
這個是最便宜
But after all, these traditions in Taiwan
但是畢竟台灣的這些傳統
traditional craftsmen
傳統的手工藝的人
some things he doesn't want to give up
有一些他不願意放棄
improve improve
改良 改善
Then the galaxy is reshaped and then spiced
然後銀河再造型再香料
What about the volunteer process and method?
在那個志工 工序工法方面呢
improve and then
改善 然後呢
can create a new market
可以開創一片新的這個市場
This corresponding park
這相應園區
this place is available
這個地方有空
Google it yourself
你們自己上網Google一下
can go to play
可以去玩
it becomes a
它那邊變成一個
one of those playgrounds
一個那個遊樂場所
DIY also has
DIY也有
That restaurant also has hotels and B&Bs
那個餐廳也有旅館 民宿
have everything
什麼都有
This is a
這是一個
A self-contained industry after transformation
一個轉型以後的自相的產業
then these what
然後這些什麼
ceramics
陶瓷還有減綿
Because inside our traditional temple
因為我們傳統的廟宇裡面
The process required
所需要用到的工藝
Now there is also this new development
現在也有這個新的發展
This is flat creation industry
這個做平創產業
come out
出來
you come again
你再來
didn't you just say
剛剛不是說
look far away
遙遙相望
There is a new statue of Mazu
有一尊新造型的媽祖像
Here's the Meadows Citizen in Northport
這是在北港的草地公民
Follow the two of Nei Zun Meizhou Island to look at each other
跟著內尊梅州島的兩個搖搖相望
Because this statue was sent by Meizhou Island
因為這一尊是梅州島送的
Then Meizhou Island Nei Zun was sent by Beigang
然後梅州島內尊是北港送
They are relatives of Dijie
他們帝傑這個親戚
Again
再來一次
Then this new model of Mazu
然後這個新造型的媽祖
It is now used by China
現在就變成是中國用來
And focus on promoting a version of Mazu
而重在宣傳媽祖的一個版本
everywhere
到處各地
Look at that shape
你看都是那個造型
Now they don't enshrine
現在他們裡面也不供奉
Our traditional sitting Mazu
我們傳統那種坐著的媽祖
Black
黑色的
So what they worship is this
所以他們供奉的是這種
This is Mazu in Macau
這個是在澳門的媽祖
Macau returned to China in 1999
澳門可是1999年回歸
Mainland?
大陸嘛
So the mainland will send them
所以大陸也就送他們
And this is one time I went to Australia for a meeting
然後這是有一次我去澳洲開會
The local friend told me
當地的那個朋友跟我說
Over there I used to have a statue of a goddess in Chinese
那邊我曾經過有一尊女神像中文
you go and see
你們去看看
He said he couldn't figure out what kind of idol that was.
他說他也搞不清那個是什麼神像
let's go see
我們去看看
really boss
真的是巴主
OK, it's concluded because time
好 結論了因為時間
The Study of Folk Beliefs
民間信仰的研究
what we're saying is
我們要說的是
he is not a dead faith
他不是一個死的信仰
Nor is it a non-us related
也不是一個跟我們無相關的
an irrelevant belief
不相關的一個信仰
he can be
他可以是
he can be society's reaction
他可以是社會的反應
It is a response to social and cultural changes
就是社會文化變遷的反應
What about research on Mazu belief?
那媽祖信仰的研究呢
It can be said to be a benchmark for the study of folk beliefs
可以說是民間信仰研究的一個標桿
because of the beliefs of other gods
因為其他的神明的信仰
hasn't happened yet
還沒發生的
Mazu beliefs all happened first
媽祖信仰都先發生了
After the Matsu belief first carried out this cross-strait exchange
馬祖信仰先進行這個兩岸的交流之後
All subsequent gods have gone to mainland owners
後續的所有的神明都去大陸業主了
Look at the Emperor Baosheng
你們看後來那個保生大帝
What Guangze Zunwang Sansan King
什麼廣澤尊王 三三國王
And the emperor of Xuanyuanjiao
還有那個宣元教的那個皇帝
Emperor Xuanyuan and that Emperor Guan Sheng
宣元皇帝 還有那個關聖帝君
and all the gods
還有所有的神明
Now the plane on the two sides of the strait
現在那個兩岸的飛機上面
If you see the one holding that god
如果你們看到抱著那個神明的
Don't be weird, and don't look at people, it's impolite, right?
不要奇怪 也不要去看人家很不禮貌對不對
You knew he was going to the countryside. That's right.
你就知道他在進鄉就對了
Then the airlines first forbade them to take country slaves with them
然後最先航空公司不准他們帶鄉奴 帶鄉上去
Because that violates the aviation safety law
因為那個違反航空安全法呀
But not now, so many believers want
但是現在不行啦 這麼多信徒要
So it's just that they have another way
所以呢 就是他們有另外的做法
There is an alternative to that
有那個替代品的做法
There is still time to pass
還有通關的時候
If you hide something inside the idol
你如果在神像裡面偷裝什麼
Because isn’t God wearing many layers of clothes?
因為神不是穿了好多衣服一層一層的嗎
What to put in it, when the Chinese customs refuse to give it
裡面放什麼 那個中國海關不讓給的時候
Not even now, as long as you are a believer in Taiwan
現在也都不行 只要是你台灣信徒
Then you walk with that idol in your arms
然後你抱著那個神像走 一路
Go through the customs all the way and go inside.
一路就這樣通關進到裡面去
Customs officers in the mainland did not dare to stop
大陸的海關人員也不敢阻攔
yes he wants to buy a place
有 他要買一個位置
Because when you get on the plane, the gods also make a position
因為你上機艙的時候 神明也做一個位置
also buy a place
也要買一個位置
so internet safety belt
所以 網路安全帶
yes or you will fall
要啦 不然你會掉下來
So the other gods haven't seen it yet
所以其他神明還沒看到
You have already seen wave after wave on Mazu belief
你已經先在媽祖信仰上面看到 一波一波的
It is because Mazu belief is so prosperous in Taiwan
就是因為媽祖信仰在台灣是那麼興盛
He is close to our life again
他又貼近我們的生活
All aspects of your life will drive him
你所有的生活面都會帶動他
He's also driven by you so he responds
他也會被你帶動 所以他會反應
Therefore, the study of Matsu belief is almost a benchmark for tomorrow's belief study
所以馬祖信仰的研究幾乎是明天信仰研究的一個標竿
The other is that our faith study is to put it back
另外就是說我們的信仰研究是把它放回
Looking at the context of this social life
這個社會生活的脈絡裡面來看
OK, I'll just report here
好 我就簡單報告到這邊
Thank you very much Dr. Zhuang for the wonderful
非常感謝莊博士的精彩
In just one hour, he
他用短短一個小時的時間
Tell us about the origin and development of this Matsu belief
告訴我們這個馬祖的信仰的源流發展
Finally, some future
最後也點到未來的一些
That is to say, in fact, I sound like Western religious culture
就是說其實我聽起來就是跟西方的宗教文化
full of different
滿不一樣的
Our Matsu is almost integrated into our current life
我們這個馬祖幾乎就是融入我們現在的生活裡面
ok we can open now
好 我們現在可以開放